<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aqua genitalis a discourse concerning baptism. First delivered in a sermon at Alhallows Lumbardstreet, Octob. 4. 1658. and now a little inlarged. Into which is since inserted, a brief discourse to perswade to a confirmation of the baptismal-vovv. / By Symon Patrick, B.D. minister of the Gospel at Battersea.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2142_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868950</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868950</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121307</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 244:E2142[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aqua genitalis a discourse concerning baptism. First delivered in a sermon at Alhallows Lumbardstreet, Octob. 4. 1658. and now a little inlarged. Into which is since inserted, a brief discourse to perswade to a confirmation of the baptismal-vovv. / By Symon Patrick, B.D. minister of the Gospel at Battersea.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R White, for Francis Tyton at the three Daggers in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With initial errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>pp. 100-104 = appendix.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aqua Genitalis:</hi> A DISCOURSE CONCERNING BAPTISM.</p>
            <p>Firſt delivered in a Sermon at <hi>Alhallows Lumbardſtreet,</hi> OCTB. 4. 1658. and now a little inlarged.</p>
            <p>Into which is ſince inſerted, a brief Diſcourſe to perſwade to a Confirmation of the BAPTISMAL VOVV.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> SYMON PATRICK, <hi>B.D.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Butterſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 2.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Circumciſion is that of the heart, in the Spirit, and not in the letter.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton</hi> at the three <hi>Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:2"/>
            <head>Be pleaſed to correct theſe faults that have eſcaped the care of the Printer.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle, <hi>pag</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 13. read <hi>ſent.</hi> In the Preface, p. 3. <hi>l.</hi> 4. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 10. <hi>l.</hi> 5. t. <hi>notice.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. <hi>marg.</hi> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 16. <hi>l.</hi> 17. t. <hi>Obedience. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</hi> l. 21. <hi>of it; we may.</hi> In the Treatiſe. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 9. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ib.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 22. <hi>l.</hi> 6 r. <hi>And.</hi> p. 34. <hi>l</hi> 27. r. <hi>Dilherrus.</hi> p 35. <hi>l.</hi> 8. r. <hi>Grabern.</hi> p. 38. <hi>l.</hi> 20. r. <hi>as for.</hi> p. 40. <hi>marg.</hi> r. <hi>L.</hi> 1. p. 41. <hi>l.</hi> 26. r. <hi>we are.</hi> p. 47. <hi>l.</hi> 12. r. <hi>will</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>well.</hi> p. 75. <hi>l.</hi> 7. r. <hi>ſtrengthner.</hi> l. <hi>ult.</hi> 1. <hi>for me.</hi> p. 79. <hi>l.</hi> 19. r. <hi>creditable.</hi> p. 88. <hi>l.</hi> 8. r. <hi>all the Goſpel.</hi> p. 91. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>marg.</hi> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not needfull to detain thee with many words about the Matter or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe:</hi> The Matter I am ſure will commend it ſelf to thee, if thou wilt be pleaſed ſeriouſly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to read, and conſider it. And as for the Author, I muſt not without diſpleaſing him, ſay any thing of him, but only give thee the true reaſon of the Publication of this Diſcourſe: which I dare affirm on my cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit is not from any itching deſire to appear in print, and I believe none that know him, but will bear witneſs with me in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. The ſubſtance of it was at my earneſt entreaty firſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and afterwards for mine, and the ſatisfaction of ſome other friends, tranſcribed, and becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:121307:4"/>
I would not give him the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of tranſcribing ſo many Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies as were deſired, and he not judging it ſafe to give liberty to other Copies that were not writ by himſelf, and I, together with others, judging it of ſingular uſe for the begetting of right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Baptiſm in theſe days of ſo much conteſt; I made it my further requeſt it might be printed, and with his leave have now ſet it abroad, which I could not in civility do without this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he hath done me herein, which I doubt not but will prove as real a ſervice to thee, and the Truth. Whatever advantage thou ſhalt reap from it, aſcribe the praiſe to God, and look upon thy ſelf as concern'd to pray for the Author, and let him alſo have a ſhare in thy prayers, who hath been an occaſion of ſo great a good unto thee, and is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant in the Lord, E. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL things coming <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>1</label> from one Fountain and Father of being, there muſt needs be ſome marks and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of himſelf upon the face of every one of them, and they cannot but have ſome cognation with, and reſemblance of each other, as things that proceed out of the ſame womb of the eternal goodneſs. Material beings &amp; ſpiritual one would think were at the greateſt diſtance, and yet they challenge a kindred one with the other, and there are lines and ſtrokes in theſe outward ſhapes, that expreſs ſomething of thoſe internal and inviſible beauties. All this world below is but the image of the
<pb facs="tcp:121307:5"/>
world above, and theſe corporeal things are but pictures (though pale indeed &amp; dull,) of things ſpiritual, as the Tabernacle of God among his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient people may inform us. For as ſome modern Philoſophers call the Londſtone a <hi>Terrella,</hi> or <hi>little Earth</hi> which draws ſimilar bodies into its Embraces; ſo <hi>Philo</hi> ſome where calls the Tabernacle <hi>a little World,</hi> a ſmall image of the whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, (the moſt holy reſembling the higheſt Heavens, the holy place, the upper Regions where the Lights of the world are placed, and where God hath ſet a Tabernacle for the Sun, &amp; the outward court, the lower parts and skirts, as we call them of this world,) whereby God would ſhew that he could not dwell in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made with hands, but that the whole world was his Temple, the ſouls of men his Altars, Love his holy fire, and all men his ſacrifices. And ſo the Apoſtle calls it<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 9.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a worldly ſanctuary, perhaps in this ſenſe that I have mentioned.
<pb facs="tcp:121307:5"/>
Now the ſame Apoſtle afterwards tells us, <hi>verſ. 23, 24.</hi> That this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and Appurtenances were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Patterns,</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> or <hi>Copies</hi> of things in the Heavens; and ſo doth the whole Scripture draw repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and images of the other world and things to come, from the Sun, the Stars, the Light, the Feaſts, and ſuch like things that are in this, wherein we inhabit.</p>
            <p>Man is made by God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>2</label> (as one ſpeaks) of kin to two worlds,<note place="margin">Fibula utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mundl.</note> the knot as it were that ties them both together, or the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton that faſtens then one to the other. He lives in the confines of each, and with his mind is capable to look into the world of ſouls and ſpirits, and with his body he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with theſe material images. God therefore hath thought fit to teach his mind the things of the one, by the Miniſtry of his bodily ſenſes which have acquaintance only with the other. And beſides, the whole
<pb facs="tcp:121307:6"/>
book of the Creatures (every letter of which is full of God,) he hath alwayes given man ſome ſpecial leſſons and documents by outward Characters, which he hath more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly cut and ingraven to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his mind with ſpiritual noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For though man be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as I ſaid, in the confines of both worlds, yet he is bred up among ſenſible Creatures, and contracts acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance here, before his ſoul is grown ſo high as to take any notice of things above; and therefore he being moſt affected with the bodies companions, it is the ſingular care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God to teach him by ſuch things as are moſt familiar to him, which he hath done in all ages of the world. It was a cuſtome among the Antients, (as they report,) before the knowledge of Letters and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to ſing their Laws, leſt they ſhould forget them, which was in uſe among ſome people near to <hi>Scythia</hi> in the days of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> And this is one reaſon why the
<pb facs="tcp:121307:6"/>
Pſalms are in verſe, becauſe they would be the better remembred, and more ſafely repoſited, being a Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of ſpiritual Learning. They knew well enough that what affects the ſenſes, and runs ſmoothly, is moſt regarded, and we our ſelves ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that Rithms which make a pretty noyſe or gingle, are ſooner fixed in peoples minds then words in proſe: Seeing then that outward things do ſo notably teach us, and the more any thing ſolicits any of our ſenſes, the more acceptable it is unto us, God hath been pleaſed ſo to deal with man, that he ſhall not want ſuch leſſons.</p>
            <p>This manner of Diſcipline may be deduced from the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to the Second. For God placed the firſt man in a Paradiſe, a fair and beautifull Garden, abounding with all manner of fruits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was but a Type of the coeleſtial paradiſe above, that is watered with ſtreams of Light from the face of God, and rivers of pleaſures from his heart, in the midſt
<pb facs="tcp:121307:7"/>
of which the Son of God is the tree of life. An image I ſay God gave him of Heaven, but none as yet of Hell, becauſe man was made to be happy. So God likewiſe gave him a Commandment (the matter of which was outward and ſenſible) of abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one tree in the Garden, which was but a document of the ſubjection he did ow to his Creator, and of the tenure whereby he held all his injoyments. After his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience men were ſome way or other directed by him to make offerings to God of their beaſts and fruits, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements of their dependance and homage, and adumbrations of the Sacrifice of that ſeed that was newly promiſed. In proceſs of time, when obedience grew cold, and their thoughts (its like) of another life but dull, God took <hi>Enoch</hi> to himſelf when he was but <hi>365.</hi> years old, to teach them by themſelves, as well as other things, that there was another life, and a reward that remained for thoſe that walked with God, which
<pb facs="tcp:121307:7"/>
was hetter then the longeſt term of years in theſe earthly poſſeſsions. But wickedneſs ſtill increaſing, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the world by a Deluge of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which was but a ſhadow of the dreadfull ſhowers of wrath, the ſtreams of fire and brimſtone that ſhould fall upon the heads of the wicked in the other life, whereby God would terrifie the new planters of the world, and give them an image of Hell, as he had done before of Heaven. But this was not a laſting viſible monument of Gods anger, and therefore in aftertimes, <hi>Sodom and Gomorrah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 7.</note> 
               <hi>and Cities about them were ſet forth for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuffering the vengeance of an eternal fire;</hi> which places lay juſt in the view, &amp; under the eye of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom God made peculiar to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, &amp; ſerved as continual marks of his dipleaſure, and inſtances of his wrath, to make them for ever to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware. That peculiar people God ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to himſelf by the ſign of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, the ſeal of the Covenant
<pb facs="tcp:121307:8"/>
that he made with them. This mark was moſt properly made in that part of their fleſh, becauſe the great promiſe to <hi>Abrah.</hi> was, that he would multiply his <hi>ſeed</hi> as the ſtars of Heaven,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> and that in his <hi>ſeed</hi> all the Nations of the world ſhould be bleſſed, and it aptly repreſent (beſides other things) that they were to be an <hi>holy ſeed</hi> unto the Lord. After this God did by two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſhadow forth unto them that his favours are at his own diſpoſal, and that they are not confer'd by nature, but by grace.</p>
            <p>In the line of <hi>Iacob,</hi> beſides that, there were many myſtical and ſecret ſignifications of his Will, which God made by ſundry perſons and actions, there were alſo many outward mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt images given of heavenly things. In the Law that <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered to them, their ſeveral waſhings, their meats, their ſacrifices (to name nothing elſe) were all ſigns of all ſorts of purity and obedience, too many now to be particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. Their offerings, and ſome
<pb facs="tcp:121307:8"/>
of their ſacrifices repreſented the obedience and ſervices of particular Chriſtians, who are made Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, but the chiefeſt of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the offering and ſacrifice of the high Prieſt of our profeſsion, which was Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>And (that I may not be tedious) when God would ſhew the greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to the world, and open moſt of Heaven, and things above, he comes &amp; dwels amongſt us in the perſon of his Son, and in an outward ſhape ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts himſelf to our eyes and ears: For in the very humanity of Chriſt ſo much of Divinity appeared, and the Majeſty, Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs of God ſo rayed forth, that he ſaith to <hi>Philip, He that hath ſeen me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>hath ſeen the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi> Yea, When God would give a Teſtimony of Jeſus to be his Son, he doth it by the viſible deſcent of the holy Ghoſt, which he ſaw <hi>coming down upon him like a Dove;</hi> as if he would tell us, that his own Son ſhall likewiſe be taught by theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:121307:9"/>
ſigns &amp; reſemblances, he being in all things to be conformed unto men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>4</label> Though our Lord therefore hath taught a Religion more full of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual notions then had been mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted before, and hath given more clear notions of things above unto mens minds then had formerly come unto them; yet he would not quite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the old manner of Diſcipline by outward things, but retains ſome of them in his Oeconomy, knowing how weak the minds of men are, and how much more eaſily they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend by ſenſe, then by themſelves. Only it is to be obſerved, that he hath made eventheſe outward things to ſpeak more plainly, and tell their meaning more diſtinctly, &amp; hath writ their inſtructions in a greater, and more legible letter then ever before.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>5</label> Baptiſm is one of thoſe Reliques, a Symbole of great and clear ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficancy, the Sacrament ef Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the ſecond birth, which it doth moſt aptly expreſs, as the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Treatiſe</hi> will ſufficiently
<pb facs="tcp:121307:9"/>
ſhew you. For the preſent it may ſuffice to ſay, that water (of all things that are eaſie to be got, and are at hand) was the moſt fit thing that can be thought on to be choſen to make an Embleme of the ſpiritual Generation. For we naturally come out of a liquid, moiſt ſubſtance, out of a ſlimy water, or in <hi>Jobs</hi> phraſe, <hi>We are poured out like milk, and then curdled in the womb like cheeſe,</hi> Job <hi>10.10.</hi> It is not unuſual in the Scripture to ſpeak of our natural procreation under the Metaphor of Water, as may be diſcerned by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting but theſe two places, <hi>Prov. 5.15, 16,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Prov. 9.17.</hi> And it is well known that while we lie in the womb, we ſwim in a ſweet liquor, and hang by the Navel in the midſt of a watry nouriſhment. <hi>Oſiris</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> (if we may believe <hi>Plutarch</hi>) were nothing in the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Muthology, but the river <hi>Nile</hi> and the earth, between which two all things were begotten.</p>
            <p>So the <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> upon the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:121307:10"/>
verſe of <hi>Pindar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thinks that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore water is to be reputed the beſt of things, becauſe out of it the other three Elements are begotten; out of the ſubtil part of it, the air is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; out of the groſſer, being curdled and compacted, the Earth; and out of the more aetherial and ſpiritous part, the Fire. But perhaps I do not well to purſue this notion ſo far, and our Saviour might not have reſpect to ſuch things as theſe. Yet this we are ſure of,<note place="margin">John 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>that we muſt be born again of water and the Spirit,</hi> and that our ſpiritual nouriſhment after Chriſt is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with in us, is compared unto water alſo, as you may ſee, <hi>John 4.14.</hi> And I cannot but likewiſe think, that he had ſome regard in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Baptiſm to the cleanſing and cooling quality that is in water; and that it excellently repreſents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, the Spirit of God to be poured forth to the purifying and waſhing us from the filth of ſin, and the blood of Chriſt to the extinguiſhing our
<pb facs="tcp:121307:10"/>
guilt, and quenching the heat of Gods anger, that might juſtly burn in our ſouls when we did remember that we were ſinners.</p>
            <p>But there have ſo many ſeveral <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>6</label> winds of Doctrine blown upon theſe Waters of Baptiſm, and ſtrove toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they are become troubled and darkened, ſo that one can ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee with any clearneſs to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of them.</p>
            <p>The great Controverſies that have aroſe about the perſons that ſhould be baptized, have ſo toſſed and agitated mens thoughts, that I doubt few have any calm and ſetled apprehenſions of the nature and end of Baptiſm it ſelf. Moſt books that treat of this ſubject are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the quarrel of <hi>Infants,</hi> that the uſe which men ought ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to make of it, is much forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. If men thought more of its true ends, they would lay aſide their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, or not manage them ſo rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they would ſoon ſee, that we are all baptized into the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb facs="tcp:121307:11"/>
and made of the ſame body, and entred by it into the ſame ſociety and community of holy and peaceable Ones. What more cool then water? What ſooner puts out all our fires? If the waters of Baptiſm (next to the blood of Chriſt) were ſprinkled upon our intemperate heats, they would aſſwage our boiling paſsions, and we ſhould contain our ſelves within the due bounds of a loving and gentle Zeal.</p>
            <p>But as I ſaid, it is but little thought of, for what Chriſt did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute this holy Rite. Some look upon it but as a cold Ceremony; and many ſpeak of it as a thing that muſt be done, becauſe Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but cannot tell to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and others glory in it as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, but little underſtand any thing of duty that it requires of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">L. 31. c. 2.</note>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> tells of a water in <hi>Cilicia</hi> which is called (he ſaith) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Mind,</hi> becauſe it will make their ſenſes that drink it ſubtil and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive.
<pb facs="tcp:121307:11"/>
               <hi>Suidas</hi> on the contrary ſaith, that it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>want Wit,</hi> becauſe it makes people fooliſh, and takes away their underſtanding. Such a different eſteem do men ſeem to have of theſe waters of Baptiſm, while ſome who ſeem wiſe, deſpiſe them as of no efficacy, and uſe them only in compliance with ſimple people; and others make them ſuch heavenly waters, that they doubt not at all, but being baptized, they are wiſe enough unto ſalvation; but both of them are agreed in this, to underſtand no Engagement that is laid upon us by them, and to expect that what they can do, ſhould be wrought alone by them, without any help or aſsiſtance from our ſelves. And we find the greateſt multitude of that ſort, who do glory in Baptiſm, as the Jews did boaſt of Circumciſion, who ſay in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, what <hi>Julian</hi> (its like falſly) makes <hi>Conſtantius</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">In his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>That our Religion requires nothing of the greateſt ſinners, but only this,</hi> Waſh, <hi>and thou art clean from all
<pb facs="tcp:121307:12"/>
thy foul crimes; and if thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them again, do but knock thy breaſt, and beat thy head, and all is well.</hi> But <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> might have anſwered him, and gives us all another leſſon in his Dialogue with the <hi>Jew;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>What good doth that Baptiſm that ſcours the skin only, and makes the body white? Baptize your ſelves from anger, and from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, from envy and hatred, and then behold your body is clean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſign and ſeal of Gods great bleſsings, and ſo it is of our promiſe to him of Obedience, upon condition then that we own this Covenant when we underſtand it, and keep our ſelves ſtrictly and religiouſly to the terms of it. We may ſay of theſe waters, as <hi>Euripides</hi> of the ſea (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the accaſion of <hi>Plato</hi>'s recovery by the ſalt waters in <hi>Aegypt</hi>)
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
They waſh away and heal all the
<pb facs="tcp:121307:12"/>
evil diſeaſes of men.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vitruvi.</hi> L. 8. cap. 3.</note> But otherwiſe they will be like ſome waters in <hi>Thrace,</hi> in which whoſoever waſhes, he certainly dies.</p>
            <p>I have therefore adventured to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>7</label> expoſe to the world a few of my green and unconcocted thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Argument, and to repreſent what I conceive to be the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Baptiſm, which is nothing dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the ſenſe of the Church of God. There are a multitude of Books I know in the world, and men complain of it; they that do, may let this alone; and of others I may eaſily obtain a pardon for putting my ſelf into the crowd, ſince I take up but a little room, and make but a very ſhort ſtop in their paſſage to better Authors. Others (it may be ſaid) might have been better allowed to have handled this matter. I think ſo too; and believe there are great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that underſtand better, and multitudes that underſtand as much, and ſome that can inlarge theſe things that are here ſaid, into more
<pb facs="tcp:121307:13"/>
perſpicuous and profitable diſcourſes: and I dare not ſo much as flatter my ſelf, that I am able to lead the way to any of them; if I may provoke them to do better, I think my labour well beſtowed. I am ſenſible that the images of truth make but a weak and wateriſh impreſsion upon my mind, but they may draw more lively pictures of themſelves upon other ſouls, and let them give us a Copy of their conceptions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>8</label> Since the preaching of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, it came ſo ſtrongly into my mind (by taking notice of ſome diſcourſes abroad) to inſert ſomething of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, that I could not well put away thoſe thoughts, and ſo I have let them take their place in the body of the Sermon, by way of perſwaſion to a more hearty, and open owning of the baptiſmal Covenant.</p>
            <p>Thereby men will aſcend from <hi>Water</hi> unto <hi>Wine;</hi> from a weak eſtate, to a more ſtrong and manly conſtitution: and God will not only ſprinkle clean water upon their faces,
<pb facs="tcp:121307:13"/>
but even <hi>lay his hands</hi> upon their heads, thereby taking more firm hold of them, and apprehending them for his own, and conferring his bleſsings more abundantly on them, now that they put themſelves into his hands, to be directed and ruled in all things by him, as thoſe that are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his power.</p>
            <p>I dare not keep you any longer in the entry, for fear you grow weary, and loth to ſtep over the Threſhold of the next leaf, and look into the main Building. And there I ſhall not ſtay your eyes long, for my furniture being little, it was not wiſdom to make the houſe too wide and ſpacious.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:14"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121307:14"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 16.33.</hi> ult.</bibl>
                  <p>And was baptized, he and all his, ſtraightway.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſt having given a Command to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>to go and teach</hi> (or diſciple,) <hi>all Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>baptizing them in the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</hi> We find in this ſtory of their Acts, (wherein ſome of their travels are related,) that as ſoon as they had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded any perſons to be Chriſtians, immediately they received them into their fellowſhip, by this Ceremony of waſhing them with water. A Truth which among all the Diſputes about <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> one would think ſhould never have been quarrelled; yet there have been
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121307:15"/>
thoſe buſie phanſies in the world that have called this into Queſtion,<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>de haereſ.</hi> 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59.</note> and would perſwade us that our Saviour in thoſe words intended not any ſuch wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing with water, and no other <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> is to be owned, but that of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>But ſo men may ſay, if they pleaſe, that when <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch went into the water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>he baptized him with fire.</hi> If the Apoſtles could underſtand our Saviours meaning, thoſe men are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently refuted by their practiſe; for though our Saviour Baptized none that we read of, but with the Spirit; (and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will have a hard task to obtain this preheminence for <hi>Peter,</hi> that he received the Baptiſm of water at Chriſts hands:) yet it will be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pains to prove that his Apoſtles and their Succeſſors after them did initiate, and admit Diſciples in that manner.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this, there are others that (left the world ſhould be quiet,) do ſtart a new Queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Command of our Lords ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any further, then to the firſt proſelyting of the Nations, or ought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121307:15"/>
now to be followed among Chriſtian people? who might have ſpared the labour of making ſuch a doubt, unleſs they could give us ſome ground to think, that that part of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was after revoked, or then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to ſuch a time, and likwiſe ſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expound thoſe following words, <hi>I am with you alwayes to the end of the world,</hi> and ſhew us why the work of the new birth (which the Apoſtle makes the ſignification of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi>) is not now as well as then to be ſhadowed and repreſented, Yet others will not let their wits be at reſt, but make a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquiry, Whether the words of our Saviour include in them a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or only a Permiſſion, becauſe he ſaith only <hi>Baptizing,</hi> not <hi>Baptize?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Though the conſtant practiſe of the Apoſtles in this Book related, and of the Church afterward, might well have been ſufficient to have ſilenced theſe thoughts without any further diſpute; and the following words likewiſe <hi>Teaching them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>verſe</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would have told ſuch men that their inquiry was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, unleſs it can be thought, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth not ſay, <hi>Go teach,</hi> we may
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121307:16"/>
chuſe whether we will give any further inſtruction to our people.</p>
            <p>Taking it therefore for granted, (without engaging my ſelf in ſuch queſtions,) that the words now read, do ſpeak of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by water ſtill to be retained in the Church of God; you may obſerve in them theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Rite or Ceremony uſed, and that is <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>waſhing with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſons baptized, <hi>The Jaylor, and all his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The time of its Adminiſtration, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtraight-way, inſtantly,</hi> at that hour of the night that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going ſtory was acted, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay.</p>
            <p>From which I am invited to treat of three things; Firſt, Of the Uſe and Intention of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Secondly, Of the qualities or diſpoſitions of thoſe that receive it. Thirdly, Of the time that is required to render them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fitly qualified to receive it.</p>
            <p>For the Explication of the firſt, we need find no fault with the common language, that ſaith, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121307:16"/>
notion is an outward viſible ſign and ſeal of ſome inward and inviſible grace and favour conveyed, and made over thereby unto us. But to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence it from the other Sacrament, we muſt enquire what that grace, favour and priviledge is, and ſhew how it doth ſignifie, and ſeal it between God and us. And upon due conſideration, I believe we ſhall find, that to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, expreſſeth ſomething on our part, and ſomething on Gods, both which put together, make it a foede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rite, whereby we and God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a Covenant and Agreement together, and mutually engage to the performance of ſeveral things, which are all to our behoof and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As we preſent our ſelves to the Miniſter of this Sacrament, and receive it, ſo it expreſſes ſomething done by us; and then 2. As the Miniſter (Gods Deputy or Embaſſadour,) doth receive us, and waſh us with this water, by the Authority, and into the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt; ſo it expreſſeth ſomething done by God. Both which it concerns us
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121307:17"/>
for the ſecuring of our duty, and our comfort alſo, to be acquainted withall; and therefore I ſhall ſhew you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the true meaning and intent of it on the part of the perſon baptized who offers himſelf, or is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive it: which I will lay before you in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the general notion of it, it is a profeſſion of a Religion wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we enter, and to which we engage to be faithfull and conſtant Diſciples. It is a Ceremony whereby Proſelytes are made, and all that uſe it do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by come into a new way and ſtate, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking all their old perſwaſions, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and relations wherein they were born and bred, that are contrary to, and inconſiſtent with theſe new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements. It is well obſerved by St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In nullum nomen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gionis, ſeu v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tari p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſant h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> al quo Signaculorum ſeu Sacramentorum viſib lium Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oll g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atur. <hi>adv. Fauſt. l. 19. cap. 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That men can be aſſociated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in no Religion, whether true or falſe, unleſs they be combined by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon tie of ſome viſible ſigns and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their profeſſion.</hi> Which the world hath found by ſo long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121307:17"/>
to be true, that I need not be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to prove it. The Jews it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt were differenced from others by Circumciſion, and (as their Doctors tell us,) entred into Covenant with God, not only by it, but by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, together with a ſacrifice unto him. And when a <hi>Heathen</hi> would become a <hi>Jew,</hi> and undertake their Religion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Pux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torf. Lex. Rab. vocab. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſo repoſe himſelf (as their phraſe is,) under the wings of the divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, he was to be circumciſed, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and offer Sacrifice; for which <hi>Maimon</hi> (as ſundry Learned men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve out of him,<note place="margin">De prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſu.</note>) brings no other proof, but that <hi>Num.</hi> 15.15. <hi>As ye are, ſo ſhall the ſtranger be;</hi> ſo ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as a thing well known, that by thoſe three the <hi>Jews</hi> ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the yoak of the Law. And it is as commonly known that they ſay their mothers entred into Covenant only by Baptiſm &amp; Sacrifice, and ſo did ſome Proſelytes by thoſe (without Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,) ingage to worſhip the one God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and forſaking all Idols, to obſerve him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as that paſſage of <hi>R. Joſhuahs</hi> clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhews, (which is cited by <hi>Raymun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121307:18"/>
He is baptized,<note place="margin">Pug. Fidei Part. 3. Diſt. 3. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, <hi>Behold this is a ſtranger convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> for loe we find of our mothers, <hi>(viz. Sarah, Rebecca, &amp;c.)</hi> that they were <hi>baptized,</hi> but not <hi>circumciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſm</hi> now hath no different ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, but only we lay this Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon our ſelves, to worſhip the <hi>God &amp; Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> &amp; to come to him through his Son, &amp; to embrace that religion which he teaches us from God, which is that whereby we are diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Jews, Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> and all other people in the world, who go not to God through this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, nor own that bleſſed Goſpel that he hath delivered unto us.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould ask me, why by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we ſhould make this Profeſſion rather then any other Rite; The anſwer me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks is eaſie, if what hath been ſaid he conſidered, together with the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars that I ſhall mention after I have diſpatched this general notion of it. And beſides, it ſeems conſiderable to me, that <hi>Moſes</hi> the Mediator of the Old Covenant did receive the people into it by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and not by <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</hi> For it is not only ſaid, <hi>Exodus</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121307:18"/>
19.10. <hi>That they ſhould ſanctifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and waſh their cloaths;</hi> but it is likewiſe plain from <hi>Joſhuah</hi> 5.5. <hi>That none were circumciſed while they were in the wilderneſs,</hi> and they are not all the while reproved or rebuked for it, and were notwithſtanding within the Covenant, which was ſure by ſome Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony or other; and the Apoſtle al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. <hi>That they were all baptized into</hi> Moſes <hi>in the cloud, and in the ſea.</hi> God by the covering of the cloud, took them under his wings and protection, owning them for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they paſſing through the heart of the ſea, the waters incloſing them round about, did profeſs to truſt in God, and there to drown all the thoughts of <hi>Aegypt</hi> which ſometimes they feared, and ſometimes they loved over-much. Now as only <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and not <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was uſed, when God conducted his people by the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miniſtry of Angels, (who marched with them in the cloud,) and delivered them from the ſlavery and bondage of <hi>Aegypt</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo God thought fit to uſe no other way of making Diſciples when he ſent his own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121307:19"/>
Son to work a greater ſalvation for us, and to be the Mediator of a better Covenant with us, of which the antient <hi>Jews</hi> do not ſeem to have been altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant, when they ſay, that there ſhall be ſuch a multitude of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes in the days of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Grot.</hi> in Mat. 3.6.</note> that they ſhal be admitted by Baptiſm only without any Circumciſion. It may not be unfit to add, that all nations uſed Waſhings ſo much, that there could not be invented (one would think,) a Rite more likely to be readily received then this. The <hi>Jews</hi> it is plain, not only when they admitted perſons into Covenant, but afterwards alſo in caſe of legal pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions uſed divers Waſhings, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles phraſe is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. Three ſorts of which I find obſerved by a learned man;<note place="margin">Gaulmyn not. <hi>in</hi> vit. <hi>Moſes.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, There were their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> hath largely ſhewn that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> do not ſignifie among them alwayes the Waſhing of the whole body, which is to be obſerved againſt thoſe that make it now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. <hi>Not. Miſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. cap.</hi> 9.</note> their daily waſhings which were introduced by the <hi>Phariſees.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, There were their Baptiſms or Immerſions of the whole body into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121307:19"/>
water, which all the <hi>Jews</hi> were bound unto in their confeſſions. And thirdly, The bathings of their women which they were tied unto ſeven weeks after their delivery of a child. Unto which I may likewiſe add, that Waſhing was uſed as a token of innocency and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from ſuch guilt as might be thought to cleave to a perſon; which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſuppoſeth in that phraſe, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 26.6. and the book of <hi>Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy</hi> plainly expreſſeth, 21. 6, 7. <hi>They ſhall waſh their hands,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Our hands have not ſhed this blood, &amp;c.</hi> which perhaps <hi>Pilate</hi> would imitate, (having to do with the <hi>Jews,</hi>) when he had condemned our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.24. <hi>For he waſhed his hands before the multitude, and ſaid, I am innocent of the blood of this juſt man, ſee ye to it;</hi> as if it had been but an accidental murther, or that which he could no more help, then if a man had been killed by chance. Certain it is the Gentiles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſed Waſhings very much, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after murthers, but likewiſe in caſe of other crimes, and alſo in their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of perſons into the ſecrets of ſome of their Religions; for which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121307:20"/>
ſee<note n="(*)" place="margin">De Baptiſ cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; de Praeſcrip. cap. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to make us believe the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed this Ceremony in theſe caſes, this might make it very probable, for the Gentiles were but their Apes, and the Devil (as<note n="(†)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Apolog.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Juſt. Martyr</hi> obſerves in this very caſe of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi>) took di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Rites, and made them do ſervice in his helliſh Myſteries; They hearing (ſaith he,) the ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Waſh you, make you clean, &amp;c.</hi> would have their Worſhippers ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with water when they went into their Temples to make an offering, yea and be waſhed all over before they came thither. All which being true, our bleſſed Lord might think it fit to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate as little as he could, &amp; ſo to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate this ſignificant and innocent Ceremony to his purpoſes, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it from the <hi>Jews</hi> to be a Rite whereby to profeſs inward purity of body and ſoul, juſt as he did in the other Sacrament of the Lords Supper, wherein he hath made uſe not only of the bread and wine, but as divers have obſerved, of the accuſtomed words which the <hi>Jews</hi> then uſed at the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Supper. For ſo his Wiſdom judged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121307:20"/>
it meet to make former Rites ſerve his own ends, rather then introduce ſtrange and unheard of things which had not been known in former times. His deſign was not novelty, but truth, not his own glory, but the good of men, and ſo he conformed himſelf in this to their practiſe, which (that I may ſpeak more particularly,) is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As a profeſsion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead works, a relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing of all ungodlineſs and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, ſo as never more to be friends with them. This is taught us not only by the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> which was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred with confeſsion of ſin, and is called the <hi>Baptiſm of Repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.6, 8. Mar. 1.4.</note> and likewiſe accompanied with an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to bring forth fruits meet for Repentance, and in refuſing of which the <hi>Phariſees</hi> are ſaid to have rejected the counſel of God againſt themſelves;<note place="margin">Luk. 7.30.</note> but alſo by the exhortation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the new Converts. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Repent and be baptized every one of you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> make profeſsion of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by Baptiſm to the remiſſion of your ſins, the ſenſe of which had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121307:21"/>
pricked them in their hearts. And it is further manifeſt from all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Baptiſm. For they put off their old cloaths, and ſtript themſelves of their Garments; then they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed all over, and buried in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which notably ſignified the putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Col. 2.11.</note>) and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into a ſtate of death or mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation after the ſimilitude of Chriſt; according to the ſame Apoſtles lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage elſewhere, <hi>We art baptized into his death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.3, 4, 6.</note> 
               <hi>we are buried with him in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> knowing that our old man is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we might not ſerve ſin. All which was rendred ſtill more ſignificant by the Antients, who baptized only on the laſt day of the week at night, <hi>i.e.</hi> on the even of two Lords dayes in the year, (called therefore by <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) Becauſe Chriſt then ſay in the grave, and was about to riſe again. In conformity to whom, they by this Rite did profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be dead, and (coming out of the water,) there to leave all their ſins
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121307:21"/>
drowned and buried in that grave, never to revive again. There is one thing more (not to be forgotten,) which makes it more clear, that it was intended for a profeſsion of Repentance, &amp; that is the Renunciation which they made to the Devil, the world, and the fleſh; or the open declaration upon the queſtion propounded which they made againſt all Gods enemies, the form of which ſo many antient Authors do record, that it is vain to cite any; but the ſenſe of it was this, Do you renounce, or do you forſake the world, and all the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, follies and wickedneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? <hi>I do forſake them,</hi> ſaid the perſon to be baptized. Do you forſake the Devil, will you have never any thing to do with his works? I do forſake him, and <hi>abhor</hi> them all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto which the Apoſtle is thought to have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. when he ſpeaks of the anſwer of a good conſcience, as the Baptiſm which ſaves us, and not the outward waſhing, or putting away of the filth of the fleſh. This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this queſtion, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> and conſequently the hearty anſwer to all that is propoſed as requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121307:22"/>
to ſalvation, is that which makes Baptiſm to be valid, and of force unto us. The <hi>Jews</hi> ſay in their tradition, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood a whole week up to the neck in water, begging of God to accept of his Repentance for what he had committed. Whatſoever he did, I am ſure this Waſhing with water doth moſt fitly repreſent both our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements that we are worthy to die, and be ſwallowed up in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and our profeſsion that we will forſake all our filthineſs, if we may but be accepted unto life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a Profeſsion of faith in the <hi>Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> For we are baptized into their name, and ſo it ſignifies, either firſt that we hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily accept of the Father for our God and happineſs, to love him above all; and of the Son, for our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, as the way unto the Father; and of the Holy Ghoſt for our Sanctifier, Guide and Conductor to the Son; or ſecondly (which comes to the ſame,) that we embrace that Doctrine for our Rule which is delivered unto us from the Father, through the hands of his Son, by the Power of the Holy Spirit,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121307:22"/>
to fear all his threatnings, to relye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all his Promiſes, and to yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all his Commands as long as we live. That this profeſſion of Faith was made in Baptiſm is plain, not only from <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. where <hi>Philip</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Eunuch, If thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou mayſt be baptized,</hi> and he anſwers, <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God;</hi> but likewiſe from this, that the word <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is put for the whole Doctrine which he preached, who did baptize, as you may ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25. (knowing only the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of <hi>John,) Acts</hi> 19.3. [<hi>Into what were you baptized?</hi> and they ſaid, <hi>into Johns Baptiſm:</hi>] By which it appears, that being baptized into ſuch a name, though one ſhould ſpeak nothing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes a conſent to embrace that word which he preaches and declares to be the Will of God. Yea, Baptiſm is an <hi>open profeſſion</hi> and Declaration to all, that we are of ſuch a faith, for it is not enough that we are perſwaded of the Truth of Chriſts Religion, but we ought alſo publiquely to own it, and manifeſt to the world our belief of it, which ſeems to me to be the meaning
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121307:23"/>
of that place, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believes, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved: i. e.</hi> He that owns the faith of Chriſt in Truth, and makes a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his belief by receiving this mark of the Chriſtian Religion, he ſhall be accepted of God to life. For that was required by our Saviour of his Diſciples, that they ſhould not be aſhamed of him before men, nor be afraid to let the world know that they were his diſciples, by uſing all thoſe things whereby they were diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the reſt of men.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is a profeſſion of holineſs and obedience, and an engagement we thereby lay upon our ſelves to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all purity in body and ſoul, which is the immediate conſequent of the two former, and ſeems to be alluded unto by the Apoſtle, when he ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Such were ſome of you, but you are waſhed, but you are ſanctified,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> you have betaken your ſelves by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Baptiſm to a holy and pure Converſation: And it is more plainly expreſſed by him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>As ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> In token
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121307:23"/>
of which, and that they intended all Purity, (like thoſe in the Reavelation, who are ſaid <hi>to follow the Lamb in white,</hi>) they were preſently cloathed with white Garments when they came out of the water. From whence that day was called <hi>White Sunday,</hi> which was one of the principle times when the Antients did admit perſons to Baptiſm; and they all profeſſed hereby, that they hated the grament ſpotted with the fleſh, and would never return again to the dirty pleaſures of the world wherein they had wallowed. An antient Chriſtian Poet doth excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently expreſs it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fulgentes animas veſtis quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> candita ſignat<note place="margin">Lactantius Firm.</note>
               </l>
               <l>El groge de niveo gaudia paſtor habet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A bright garment was caſt over ſhining and gliſtering ſouls, and the Great Shepherd took no ſmall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his milk-white Lambs, whoſe outward luſtre did but ſignifie that they were become the Children of the Light, and of the day, and would have no more fellowſhip with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull works of <hi>Darkneſs, Eph.</hi> 5.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121307:24"/>
8,<note place="margin">Fileſacus. l. <hi>1.</hi> ſelect. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 10. Which place ſome would inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret of Baptiſm, called therefore by the Antients <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Illumination, of which thoſe ſplendid Garments was a fit ſignification.<note place="margin">Georg. Fhelavius annot. ad Chriſtoph. Angel.</note> The <hi>Greeks</hi> at this day put ſuch a Robe upon the Child immediately after Baptiſm, ſaying, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this lucid and immaculate Cloathing, and bring it before the Tribunal of our Lord Jeſus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, and thou ſhall have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, <hi>Amen.</hi> Certain it is, that all true Chriſtians have ever accounted this the great intent of this outward Rite of Baptiſm, to be an Ingagement to Holineſs; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſenſe of them all. Be clean, not only by the waſhing of thy body, but the purgation of thy mind. Bath and ſteep thy ſoul in holy truths, till they have fetcht out all thy filth. For even a <hi>Jew</hi> can ſay, <hi>Qui baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſine intentione, perinde eſt ac ſi non baptizatur;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. de Voyſin, de Lege div. <hi>cap. 7.</hi>
               </note> He that doth not intend that which is meant by Baptiſm, is as if he were unbaptized; for it is not dirt (ſaith he,) and excrementious adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencies that a man waſheth away, but there is a Reſemblance herein of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121307:24"/>
cleanſing of the ſoul from all filthineſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> from thoſe perverſe thoughts, and evil habits which he profeſſes to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake by bringing his ſoul to the waters of Vertue and Knowledge, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith, <hi>chap.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Thus Maimon.</hi> And therefore they well ſaid, He that comes from among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> unto us <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the ſake of any worldly vanity,<note place="margin">Buxtorf. in vocab. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he is not a Proſelyte of Juſtice; for which cauſe they uſed to examine him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the hope of gain, or honour, or compelled with fear, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to their profeſſion, and to ſearch whether there were any young man, or woman of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that the party made love unto, becauſe they would have them only out of holy ends un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake their Religion. And indeed their riſing again, &amp; coming out of the water, did likewiſe ſignifie this, that they had left their filthineſs behind, &amp; were made new men, hence-forward to ſerve God in Righteouſneſs and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all the dayes of their life.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is a Profeſsion of ſelf-denial, and taking up the Croſs if we meet with it in our Chriſtian courſe. For
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121307:25"/>
Waters ſignifie in Scripture <hi>Afflictions</hi> and <hi>Tribulations,</hi> which ſometimes go over our heads and overwhelm us. And accordingly our Saviour ſpeaking of his ſufferings,<note place="margin">Luke 12.50. Mat. 20.22.</note> ſaith, <hi>I have a Baptiſm to be baptized with,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And are you able to be baptized with the Baptiſm that I am baptized with? i. e.</hi> to take part with me in my ſufferings and indurances here in the world for Gods ſake? and immediately it follows, <hi>You ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be baptized with my Baptiſm,</hi> you ſhall be wet in blood, and baptized in your own tears and ſweat. Whoſoever puts on Chriſt, takes upon him his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and renounces (as you have heard,) to all thoſe things, though never ſo dear, that would deveſt him of his dearer Saviour, or make him falſe to that Covevant into which he doth enter. So the <hi>Samanaeans</hi> among the <hi>Indians</hi> (as <hi>Porphiry</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">L. <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>) as ſoon as they were choſen to be of the ſociety of thoſe Divines, and had that Title, they ſhaved their body, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Stole or long Robe, after which they renounced <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to all their Eſtates, never thinking of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to Wife, Children, or any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121307:25"/>
other thing, making no account of them; but wholly imploying themſelves in the things of God, (as his words are,) they lived <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without wives, or Poſſeſsions, or their former Injoyments. Such a white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I told you the Chriſtians ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time received in token of their put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on Chriſt Jeſus the Lord; with that they put on new relations, and eſpouſed another Intereſt, and did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to forſake Father, Mother, Wife, Children, Houſes, Lands, and all things elſe for his names ſake, and to call no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing theirs, but only Chriſt. Which likewiſe we cannot deny, they did very antiently repreſent, by ſigning them with the ſign of the Croſs, (innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough it is likely, till Superſtition did abuſe it,) in token of the crucified, afflicted condition into which they muſt be willing to enter, if Chriſt ſhould call them to it. And ſo we may interpret that place, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith,</hi> lay hold on Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, whereunto thou art alſo called, and haſt profeſſed a good profeſſion before many witneſſes, <hi>i.e.</hi> endure ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for Chriſts ſake, for thou art
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121307:26"/>
called unto it, and haſt profeſſed in Baptiſm thou wouldſt be his faithfull Souldier before many witneſſes, <hi>i.e.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hierom,</hi>) before the people of God and his holy Angels thou didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to the world, and all the ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and vanities thereof, and gave up thy ſelf to indure hardſhip, (as it is in another place, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3.) <hi>Like a good Sculdier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> For this cauſe it was perhaps that their <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſp. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntiq. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> funer.</note> or Fonts uſed to he made where ſome Martyrs had ſuffered, that ſo they might be put in mind they entred into a War-fare, wherein they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt unto blood, ſtriving againſt ſin. Our very firſt Incorporation into Chriſt, is in effect an Expiration to the world; and then we begin to die, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to live. As ſoon as ever we declare for Chriſt, and are liſted into his <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia,</hi> the Devil raiſeth all his forces againſt us, and we muſt not expect to march quietly to Heaven. You ſhall read of nothing but ſufferings after our Saviours Baptiſm, and moſt of the reſt of his life before, for thirty years (which we may ſuppoſe had leſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it,) the Holy Ghoſt paſſes over;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121307:26"/>
as if he would tell us, that when by Baptiſm we give our ſelves to him, and become his Children, we enter upon a ſtate of ſufferings,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.14.</note> and perhaps muſt waſh our Garments again in the blood of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>And having thus ſhewed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Ingagement that it can lay upon us, which is to lay down our lives for Chriſts ſake if he require it; I ſhall paſs to the next part of this diſcourſe, which is to ſhew what the meaning &amp; intent of it is on Gods part, &amp; what bleſsings are thereby conveyed back again to us, who thus give up our ſelves to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God by his Miniſter (that doth in his name, and by his Authority bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize,) doth receive the perſons ſo waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Injoyment of ſome privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and benefits that otherwayes are not ordinarily to be enjoyed. For what is done by his Miniſter, is as if the hand of God ſhould do it. So it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 3.23. <hi>That Jeſus came into</hi> Judea, <hi>and baptized;</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 26. The Jews ſay to <hi>John, He to whom thou beareſt witneſs, behold the ſame baptizeth:</hi> and again, <hi>cap.</hi> 4.1. It is ſaid, <hi>That Jeſus made and baptized more Diſciples then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121307:27"/>
John;</hi> yet <hi>verſe</hi> 2. We are told, <hi>That Jeſus himſelf baptized not, but his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples.</hi> That which Officers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants do by Commiſſion and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Maſter, is accounted to be his Action; And ſo,</p>
            <p>Firſt, God receiveth us hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his family, to be numbred among his people, of whom he will have a ſpecial care.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt.</hi> ſpeaks to the newly baptized, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is the ſeal (as it were,) of God upon us, his Mark and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter whereby he owns us for his ſheep, and knows us from all other, ſo as to have a more particular inſpection over us then the reſt of the world that make not this profeſſion, &amp; to indow us with certain peculiar favours, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are able to perform any part of our Duty unto him. It is the door whereby we enter into the Church, the Gate that lets us into Chriſts fold, and the firſt ſtep to fellowſhip with God and with his people. Whence it was the Font you know uſed to be placed at the door or entrance of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Auguſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> de. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tec. rud. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> to ſignifie that by this we come into the Congregation of Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but yet that by Baptiſm we are brought but to the beginning of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121307:27"/>
and muſt make a further progreſs to perfection, till we come to the holy place, and into a nearer communion with God. The Miniſter likewiſe uſed to take the Infants into his arms, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie I ſuppoſe, Gods receiving and embracing of them with a loving affection. Yea, he uſed to kiſs them, either to ſignifie that love of God to them, or that they were now of that community and body, whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle bid to <hi>ſalute one another with a holy Kiſs.</hi> And all this is ſuppoſed in the word <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> or Comers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, which clearly argues ſome relative Action of his, which is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and entertaining them graciouſly as thoſe he will have in his favour. But more particularly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Hereby God receives us into a ſtate of pardon and forgiveneſs. He aſſures us that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin ſhall not undo us, and that every ſin of our own ſhall not exclude us out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but that we ſhall have the benefit of Repentance, and an allowance to retract our follies, yea, and Grace ſo to do, if we will make uſe of it. He admits us into that Covenant of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121307:28"/>
Grace which accepts of Repentance in ſtead of Innocence, and Amendment in ſtead of an unerring Obedience. This is one of the ſpecial favours of the Goſpel, (which by Baptiſm is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned unto us,) that former Iniquities ſhall not be remembred, and that every breach of our Covenant, if there be a real chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wrought in us, ſhall not void it, and make it null, and ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all unto us. So in <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>John</hi> is ſaid to <hi>preach the Baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for Remiſſion of ſin.</hi> And <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaith, (<hi>Acts</hi> 22.16.) <hi>Ariſe, and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and waſh away thy ſins.</hi> And the Greek Church after Baptiſm, ſings thoſe words three times,<note place="margin">Georg. Fhelavius <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe iniquity is forgiven.</hi> As thoſe who came to the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> did thereby receive a diſtinguiſhing mark and character that they ſhould not be-deſtroyed in the ruine of the Nation, (in ſo much that he ſaith to the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> that deſired Baptiſm,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi>) So they that are baptized into Chriſt, do thereby receive a pledge, that no ſin which they ſtand guilty of ſhall bring the anger of God upon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121307:28"/>
their heads if they will keep his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; but all ſhall be croſſed out which they are charged with, and be like words writ in the water, that are obliterated and vaniſhed, nowhere any more to be found.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We receive hereby the Promiſe of the Spirit, the Effuſion of which,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.5.</note> is likened to the pouring out of water; and ſo is in Baptiſm moſt aptly ſignified and repreſented. <hi>I will pour</hi> (ſaith the Prophet,) <hi>waters on him that is thirſty, and floods upon the dry ground, (i. e.</hi> upon the Gentiles who were as a wilderneſs.<note place="margin">Iſa. 44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3, 4, 5.</note>) <hi>I will pour my Spirit on thy ſeed, and my bleſſing upon thy Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, and they ſhall ſpring up as among the graſs, &amp;c.</hi> In which place, that there may be a Prediction of Baptiſm, it is very probable, for thus much ſome of the <hi>Jews</hi> do acknowledge, that the Prophet ſpeaks of Gentiles that ſhould be Proſelytes, and called by the name of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and we Chriſtians know that we are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and that this Promiſe hath a reſpect to the times of the Goſpel. <hi>Raſi</hi> out of <hi>R. Nathan</hi> thus gloſſes upon the fifth <hi>verſe:</hi> There are four ſorts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121307:29"/>
here ſpoken of, one ſhall ſay, <hi>I am the Lords,</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe are they that are Proſelytes of Juſtice, or the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Converts; <hi>And another ſhall call himſelf by the name of Jacob,</hi>
               <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe are the little Ones of the ungodly; <hi>And another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand to the Lord,</hi>
               <note n="(‖)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe are the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, or the men that repent, <hi>and ſurname himſelf by the name of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe are the ſtrangers, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe that obſerved the Precepts of the ſons of <hi>Noah,</hi> and particularly renounced Idolatry; and therefore this part of the <hi>verſe</hi> is by another rendred <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they that fear God. Where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,<note place="margin">V. <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund. pug. fidei.</hi> par. 2. cap. 14.</note> that he calls one ſort of theſe Converts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the little ones,</hi> who were not thought (it ſeems,) to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet to be made members of a Church, and were not judged by their fathers admiſſion to be received, but were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly admitted by themſelves by the decree (as they tell us,) of the houſe of Judgement. And obſerve likewiſe that all theſe Proſelytes being ſaid to ſpring as it were out of the water,<note n="*" place="margin">So Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt <hi>calls the new baptized perſons</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Orat. prima &amp; ſecunda de Reſurrect.</note> theſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121307:29"/>
words may well be a Propheſie of Chriſtian Baptiſm, to which a promiſe of the Spirit is annexed, which is very well ſignified by water; for as that cleanſes and purifies from filth, ſo the Spirit of God, (called upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Holy Ghoſt,) is the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of Gods people, purging and cleanſing their hearts from all impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. This being therefore the great work of the Spirit ſo well repreſented by water, we muſt conclude, that when the Miniſter waſheth us in Gods name, God thereby promiſeth that he will be aſſiſtant to us by the holy Ghoſt, &amp; that he will ſend upon us his Grace,<note place="margin">Tit. 8.5.</note> that we may be ſaved through the waſhing of Regeneration, and the renewing of the H. Ghoſt. According to that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. the place before mentioned, <hi>But you are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but you are juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God.</hi> Where as thoſe words <hi>[In the name of the Lord Jeſus]</hi> refers to being juſtified; ſo thoſe words <hi>[By the Spirit of God,]</hi> refers to their being waſhed and ſanctified. So in that place of <hi>Ezekiel, cap.</hi> 36.25. After
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121307:30"/>
he had ſaid, <hi>That he would ſprinkle them with clean water;</hi> it follows as an expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27: <hi>A new heart will I alſo give you, and a new ſpirit will I put into you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And I will put my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes.</hi> All which doth ſufficiently ſhew that in this Waſhing with water, the Lord ingages to give the Spirit.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. orat. <hi>1.</hi> de reſur. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, We receive hereby a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Reſurrection unto life: Though we by going into the water profeſs that we are willing to take up the Croſs, and dye for Chriſts ſake; yet on Gods parts, this action of going into, and coming out of the water again, did ſignifie that he would bring ſuch perſons to live again, <hi>That he would not leave their ſoul in grave, nor ſuffer his holy one to ſee corruption.</hi> And this according to <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> (a very judicious Interpreter, who was ſo full of the Spirit of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that he dreamt ſometime that he appeared to him,) is the meaning of that difficult place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. <hi>Elſe what ſhall they do that are baptized for the dead?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> for their dead bodies. Why do they profeſs in Baptiſm, that they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121307:30"/>
believe the Article of the Reſurrection of the dead, among the reſt of the Articles of Chriſtian faith? Why are they baptized into the hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of it, of which (ſaith he) the Miniſter gives them a ſign or ſymbole, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the things themſelves that he doth, putting them in, and taking them out of the water, which is a ſign of their deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the ſtate of the dead, and their aſcending up from thence. Now what good do they receive by Baptiſm, if they ſhall not riſe again, but remain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the grave? If any think it harſh to render theſe words, <hi>For their dead bodies,</hi> by theſe, <hi>For the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their dead bodies,</hi> (which in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm we profeſs to believe,) it is only for want of skill in the ſhort manner of ſpeaking, which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> uſe. And methinks they may otherwiſe be interpreted to the ſame ſenſe more plainly after this manner, <hi>Why are they baptized for their dead bodies,</hi> i. e. <hi>for the benefit and profit of their dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies?</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denotes the end, which an Agent intends in an action. (as <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. who gave himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121307:31"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome have it, which is of the ſame force.</note> for to take away our ſins,) and there can be no end upon our dead bodies which we can have, but that they may live again; therefore for this end we are baptized, that they may riſe from the dead, which if they ſhould not, we ſhould loſe (ſaith the Apoſtle,) the great benefit which in Baptiſm was conſigned; and to what purpoſe ſhould we uſe that Rite? It may be replied, that I have already mentioned many other purpoſes which render it ſufficiently beneficial. But if it be conſidered how near ſin and death are one to the other, we ſhall conclude that ſo muſt remiſſion of ſin, and the reſurrection from the dead go together, and that if the one be not believed, we may eaſily doubt of the other, or at the beſt, we ſhall make for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs lame and very imperfect while this great puniſhment of ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> Death remains unremoved. <hi>Luther</hi> indeed in his verſion of the Bible gives ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther interpretation of this place, but ſutable to my preſent diſcourſe, which is grounded <hi>Dilheirus</hi> thinks upon that practiſe I mentioned of Baptizing in the places where the Martyrs were
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121307:31"/>
nterred. The ſenſe whereof is this, (as one that underſtands the language, interprets it to me,) <hi>What mean they to be baptized</hi> [Uber Den Toden,] <hi>over the dead? To ſtrengthen</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi> in his gloſs upon the words,) or <hi>confirm the Reſurrection;</hi> they uſed to baptize Chriſtians <hi>[<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ber den Toden grahern,]</hi> over the graves of the dead, <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention whereof was to ſhew that the ſame, the very ſelf ſame perſon ſhould riſe again.</hi> But I doubt we ſhall not find that cuſtom ſo antient as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> days, wherein there had been but few Martyrs; and therefore I wave it, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other more clear and proper. If any one like it, then from both me may conclude, that the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs of Baptiſm are like the waters of heaven, which falling upon the dry earth, and the dead roots of plants, makes them ſpring forth, and live again. It gives us aſſurance, that we ſhall not alwayes ſleep in our duſt, but ſhall ſpring up and flouriſh in a better ſoil, even the Garden of God, never to die, or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any more. And Circumciſion ſeems not to have been without this ſignification neither, for they uſed to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121307:32"/>
caſt the fore-skin cut off into a veſſel full of duſt, to ſignifie it is like, that the circumciſed perſon did renounce the Devil and his luſts, by whoſe impulſe, <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, and ſo died, and was turned again into duſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Joſeph. de Voyſin de leg. Div. <hi>cap. 7.</hi>
               </note> and that he did caſt away all that evil concupiſcence, by which death came into the world, hoping that that being buried, he ſhould attain the Reſurrection of the body, and live again. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a very antient book (the <hi>Zohar</hi>) applies a place in <hi>Job,</hi> which ſhews, though not the ſenſe of the Scripture, yet their ſenſe of Circumciſion, <hi>Job</hi> 19.26. <hi>In my fleſh I ſhall ſee God, i. e.</hi> by Circumciſion (which was the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God in their fleſh,) come to immortal life. And a tradition they have to this purpoſe, <hi>That when a man is ſigned with this holy mark,</hi> he is made worthy of the viſion of God.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is not improperly called by Divines <hi>a ſeal of all theſe things, i. e.</hi> a Rite whereby the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant between God and us is confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereby we aſſure God of our fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and he aſſures us that as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as our bodies are waſhed with water, ſo certainly will he give us of his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121307:32"/>
Grace, &amp; if we perform our undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, continually aſſiſt us with the holy Spirit, pardon our ſins, deliver us from the power of the Devil, ſave our ſouls, and at laſt raiſe our bodies out of the grave, and make them ſpiritual and immortal, and unite both body and ſoul together i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ernal Glory. That conditional Covenant of Grace and Mercy that was ſealed before indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely by Chriſts blood, is now ſealed by Baptiſm to this particular perſon which receives it. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The ſum of all is that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are regenerated and born again. It is the Sacrament of the new birth, by which we are put into a new ſtate, and change all our relations, ſo that whereas before we were only the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> we are now taken to be the Children of God; ſuch of whom he will have a fatherly care, and be indulgent and mercifull unto. We have now a relation likewiſe to Chriſt as our Head, and to the holy Ghoſt as the Giver of life and grace. Yea, herein he grants remiſſion of ſin, and we are ſanctified, and ſet apart to his uſes. We being hereby given to him,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121307:33"/>
and he accepting of us, do become his poſſeſſion and proper goods, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without being guilty of the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Robbery ſin againſt God. We are made hereby the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, the place where he, and nothing elſe is to inhabite; and being by this conſecrated to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e likewiſe then enters upon his poſſeſſion, and we are ſaid thereby to receive the holy Ghoſt; ſo that if we run into ſin, we defile his houſe, and commit the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſs and impiety, and may be ſaid very truly to do deſpite to the Spirit of God whereby we were ſanctified. <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> well ſaith, that every man is by his birth,<note place="margin">In Phaedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>One of Gods freeholds,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concludes it is as unlawfull for a man to kill himſelf, as a ſervant to run away from his Maſter, ſeeing he is not his own goods, nor can diſpoſe of his life according to his pleaſure. In this ſecond birth God is ſeized again of us, he owns us in a ſpecial manner for his Children, and we may not without committing a double murder ſin againſt him, and may be called twice dead if we do, becauſe in Baptiſm are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121307:33"/>
the beginnings of a new life, and the Spirit of life takes hold of us, and as far as is agreeable to our age and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we are renewed by the Holy Ghoſt. For Baptiſm being a beginning of our performance of our duty, God doth likewiſe in it begin proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to make good his promiſe. We may call it therefore with <hi>Cyprian, Geneta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis unda, aqua ſalutaris, &amp;c.</hi> the Laver of Regeneration; ſeeing as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body, &amp;c.</hi> whereby he intimates that the Spirit of God doth accompany this water, and therefore we muſt be in a ſort made other Creatures. I ſee no cauſe to leave this antient language which may have a very good ſenſe, and none I ſuppoſe will deny but that at leaſt a <hi>Relative change</hi> is herein made, and ſo much Grace and Favour is conferred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that we ſtand upon better terms then meer nature did inſtate us in. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> relating the manner how Chriſtians were made, (that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens might not he offended ſo much at their Religion,) ſpeaks of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. When men are perſwaded of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121307:34"/>
thing: that we teach, and promiſe to live accordingly, they faſt, and pray, and beg of God remiſsion of ſin, and then we bring them to the water, <hi>and ſo they are born again after the ſame manner that we were regenerated:</hi> to this he applyes that place, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born again, &amp;c.</hi> All things ſeem to grow out of water, and it was not unfitly made by one of the antient wiſe men, the firſt Principle of all, ſo that it may well ſignifie another birth, a new plantation in a better ſoil, which is watered by daily dews and ſhowers of Gods heavenly Grace; and in, it we may be ſaid to have changed our Patents, and all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſo as after a manner to become new Creatures.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li. paedag.</hi> cap. 7.</note> If <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi> his reading of that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. be right one would think that Chriſt was by Baptiſm admitted to his office, and had a kind of a new birth in it, <hi>Thou art my beloved Son, this day have I begotten thee. i.e.</hi> now have I appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee to thy office, now of the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> as thou art eſteemed, I declare thee the Son of God, and make thee my Vicegerent. That which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121307:34"/>
done at the Reſurrection (to which thoſe words, <hi>This day have I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee</hi> are applyed, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33.) was begun and done in ſign at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when the Holy Ghoſt likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended upon him, and anointed him unto his office. And ſo in after times they uſed to anoint the baptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with oyl, to repreſent, I ſuppoſe, that God took him to be his Son, and did beſtow upon him the Holy Spirit. But becauſe <hi>Clemens</hi> muſt be thought to have expreſſed rather the ſenſe, then the very words that were ſpoken, let us conſider only what ſucceeded our Saviours Baptiſm, and it will tell us thus much, that at that time it was that God firſt owned him openly for his Son, and it may well teach us that in Baptiſm God takes us to be his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> we are received under his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, are, and ſhall be indued with this Holy Spirit, according as it follows in him; Chriſt was our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar or Pattern; and being <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are illuminated; and being illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, we are made ſons; and being made ſons, we are compleated; and being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, we are made immortal.</hi> There is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121307:35"/>
nothing wanting after we are baptized to the injoying the whole of this, but that we be faithfull in Gods Covenant, and follow the conduct of Gods illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating and holy Spirit, till we be made Poſſeſſors of that Immortality, unto which in Baptiſm we have a Title given us. The antient Chriſtians ſpeak of high Illuminations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall God pleaſed then to grace Baptiſm; I make no queſtion but they ſpeak as they felt, and that they talk not of a ſtrange change then wrought which never was; but if any ſay, that thoſe great Communications of the Holy Ghoſt were proper to that time when Chriſt did moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly atteſt to the Truth of his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions for the conviction of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, I think ſo alſo: for young plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations needed larger effuſions of the heavenly dews to water and cheriſh them. But yet we may conceive that there may be ſtill ſome operations of that ſpirit in mens hearts at Baptiſm, though ſecret &amp; inſenſible unto us; and I profeſs my ſelf one of thoſe that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to believe very highly of Chriſts preſence with all his own ordinances;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121307:35"/>
though if any cannot ſavour this, I will not contend, nor fight in the dark, but deſire the other things may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained which are certain, and then there will be ſufficient ground to think that it is not indifferent, whether we be baptized or no; and that it is not a naked Ceremony that neither doth good not harm, as ſome men ſeem to ſpeak againſt the conſtant ſenſe of the people of God. And thus much may ſuffice concerning my thoughts of the firſt particular, wherein you have had a ſhort account of the intent, uſe and benefit of Baptiſm. It remains that ſpeak a few words of the other two particulars in the text, and ſhew in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Who are the perſons to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text will not let us doubt but all thoſe who are willing to embrace Jeſus as the Chriſt, and the Son of the living God, and to give themſelves up to his inſtruction and teaching, are thus to be initiated and entred into his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Only it is ſcrupled, whether thoſe that cannot expreſs ſuch a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121307:36"/>
nor make any ſigns of it are ſo to be admitted, and therefore all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are by ſome excluded from theſe waters, as ſubjects uncapable, either to make any ſuch profeſſion and ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or receive from God any ſuch benefit.</p>
            <p>This point hath been ſo ſifted even to the very bran, that I cannot think mine eyes ſo acute as to diſcern any little Argument to lie ſtill neglected that I ſhould be able to boult out. The cuſtom of the Church hath been plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is accounted the beſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of a doubtfull law; And the Scriptures have been ſearched in theſe late times (more I think then ever,) by many learned Authors in every ones hands, and to ſuch excellent purpoſe, that if I were able to plead the Infants title ſtrongly, my defence might be ſpared.</p>
            <p>I will therefore briefly diſmiſs this head with theſe four conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That if there were any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in this perſons family, it is certain they were baptized, <hi>for he was baptized, he, and all his.</hi> It is doubtfull indeed, whether there were any or no; yet it is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121307:36"/>
conſiderable (eſpecially in conjunction with other Arguments,) that neither here, nor any where elſe in the whole Scripture are they excepted, (and it is ſcarce to be thought that all of the families baptized were without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,) nor is there one word that tends to the excluding of them from Baptiſm. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, I conſider that Infants are capable to be ingaged and profeſſed, and likewiſe to be received into the Grace and favour of God.</p>
            <p>Baptiſm may be looked on either as a ſign of what we are to be in our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture courſe, and what God hath done, and will do for us, and ſo all muſt grant that Infants are as capable as others to receive it; or ſecondly, As a ſeal of the truth of God, under which notion we ordinarily conceive it, and then they are as capable likewiſe as grown men to have any thing conveighed and ſealed unto them, upon ſuch conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons afterwards to be performed; or thirdly, As an Obligation whereby we are tyed to perform thoſe conditions; and fourthly, As a priviledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are actually inſtated into ſome
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121307:37"/>
Favours and Injoyments; and if any affirm that in theſe two regards they are uncapable, let them remember that Children may be bound by deeds drawn up and ſealed between two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before they underſtand any thing at all, and that a Child may be crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Cradle, and it will ſtand good to all purpoſes. A Parent may contract with God on his childs behalf, no otherwiſe then a Guardian doth in the behalf of a minor or one under age, which he cannot afterward retract when he is out of his Pupillage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuſtice, and being lyable to the Law, if the contract be judged to be to his behoof and benefit. As in the Interpretation of Law that is an Act of the Pupil, or child, which is done in its name, and for its good by his Tutor or Guardian; ſo may God be pleaſed graciouſly and favourably to accept of this Act of the Parent laying ſuch an Obligation upon the child, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it for the childs own Act and Deed, ſo conferring his graces upon it, and expecting performance of Faith and Obedience, and looking upon it as ſo ingaged, that it ſhall be properly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121307:37"/>
ſaid to break a Vow and Covenant, if it ſin againſt him. And this will ſtill be clearer from a third conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That Children are in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Parent, and they have a <hi>Jus</hi> or Right unto them, ſo as they have to any other things that are their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per goods. They may therefore make an offering of them to God, and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them to his uſes, as well as Land or Money and there is no queſtion but God will accept of them as of any thing elſe that they conſecrate to him, and take them for his portion, ſo that it ſhall be a ſacrilegious Act for theſe Infants hereafter to alienate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from him, and convert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the uſes and ſervice of any other.</p>
            <p>This the Denyers of infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm cannot deny, that it is very fit Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhould by ſolemn prayers and profeſſion devote and conſecrate their children to God and make an open ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them before all to his ſervice, only they would not have it done by waſhing with water, which is as much as to grant that they would have the thing done, but not the Ceremony or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121307:38"/>
Rite uſed, and that they are capable of the thing ſignified, but not of the ſign, of the greater matter, but not of the leſs; and as it ſeems to me they make a Controverſie where there need be none; for if they are to be devoted to God, Baptiſm being the way wherein we devote our ſelves to him and being ſo ſignificant of our Duty, it is the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt way wherein to devote our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to his uſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Chriſt may well be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to include them when he bids his Diſciples <hi>Go and baptize all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the name of the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for that was no more then a commiſſion to go and make Proſelytes, and ingage them by Baptiſm in Chriſts Religion. Now I intimated before that there were young ſtrangers admitted by the Jews, <hi>i. e.</hi> Infants or <hi>little Children</hi> were made Proſelytes to their way of Worſhip, and it is plain that all were baptized into <hi>Moſes in the ſea and in the cloud;</hi> both old and young, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants as well as the grown men paſſed through the water, and were all cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the cloud, and likewiſe <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ſunt ampliandi,</hi> where none are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121307:38"/>
favours and benefits are to be inlarged unto all; and to ſpare further labour of a long diſcourſe, let me only remember you how <hi>Moſes</hi> did take the Children into Covenant with God, as well as the reſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. <hi>You ſtand this day all of you before the Lord your God your Captains of your Tribes, your Elders, and your Officers, with all the men of Iſrael, your little Ones, your wives,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt enter into Covenant with the Lord thy God, and into his oath which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day.</hi> Why ſhould we not then think that the Mediatour of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant did include theſe little Ones, as well as others in that univerſal expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that he would have them enter into Covenant with God? If any ask why our Saviour did not then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mention them? the Anſwer will be eaſie, That there was no need for him to expreſs every particular ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Baptiſm, ſeeing it was ſo well known before by the common practiſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by the former Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and therefore his chief intent in thoſe words was to tell them in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121307:39"/>
what manner and form they ſhould now baptize, <hi>viz.</hi> in the name of the Father, Son and H. Ghoſt, which had not been yet uſed, but now was to be every where practiſed. I have no mind to add more, but beſeech the Lord, that all thoſe who diſpute againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm, may behave themſelves like men baptized, and remember that humility, modeſty and peaceableneſs of ſpirit are great Doctrines in the Chriſtian ſchool; and that if ſo many good and learned men have erred (as they think,) then ſo may they.</p>
            <p>A few words concerning the third general Head of our diſcourſe, may perhaps lend a little further light to this buſineſs, and manifeſt that there is not ſo much required as ſome ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, to qualifie and capacitate a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Baptiſm. For,</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſaid here, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſtraight way, immediatly,</hi> without any further proof he was baptized. If you look back, you ſhall find that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> being cloſe Priſoners at <hi>Philippi,</hi> there was about mid-night a great Earth-quake, that made both the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and the Jaylor alſo ſhake, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121307:39"/>
opened both the doors of the Priſon, and of the heart of the Keeper; for this ſtrange trembling of the earth, it is very likely cauſed him to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that theſe were divine perſons, for whom ſuch a wonder was wrought, and ſo to come trembling before them, and inquire what he muſt do to be ſaved? They told him,<note place="margin">Verſ. 29, 3.</note> that he muſt believe on the Lord Jeſus, and accordingly ſpake to him the Word of the Lord,<note place="margin">Verſ. 31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> proved to him that Jeſus was the Son of God, and taught men the true Religion, and way to life. The very ſame hour he took them, and waſhed their ſtripes, and then was waſhed himſelf in the name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>By this it will appear, that though a Profeſſion of Faith be required, yet not a diſtinct belief of every thing in Chriſts Religion, for that could not in the ſpace of an hour be comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; He therefore having a general knowledge that Jeſus was the Son of God, and a Teacher ſent from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to do men great good, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing a readineſs to be taught by him, was received by Baptiſm into
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121307:40"/>
Chriſts ſchool to learn of him. That ſuch a knowledge, together with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of their fore-paſt evil life, did ſufficiently qualifie for Baptiſm; you may ſee by conſulting theſe places, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. All the Sermon of the Apoſtle tends to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but to prove that Jeſus whom they crucified, was the promiſed ſeed, which he demonſtrates from his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the effects of it, that abundantly declared he was made Lord and Chriſt. <hi>Verſe</hi> 36. When this was cleared to them, their hearts were pricked, to think what they had done, and he exhorts them to repent of it, and receive Baptiſm, which three thouſand of them immediatly did, as you read <hi>verſe</hi> 41. <hi>And continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine. Verſe</hi> 42. <hi>i.e.</hi> learning of that Religion, to which they ſaw ſo much reaſon to addict themſelves. So <hi>Acts</hi> 8.35. We find that <hi>Philip</hi> preached Jeſus to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and required only this profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of him. <hi>Verſe</hi> 37. <hi>That he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with all his heart, that Jeſus is the Son of God, and then he went down into the water with him, and baptized
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121307:40"/>
him.</hi> And again, <hi>cap.</hi> 18.5. <hi>Paul</hi> was preſſed in ſpirit, and teſtified to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that Jeſus was Chriſt; and then <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>Criſpus believed on the Lord, with his whole houſe, and many of the Corinthians hearing, believed, and were baptized.</hi> So in all other places, you will find there was ſo little ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their preaching and baptizing. that they could not well be taught more then this, that he was the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, or Chriſt that was expected, and that all muſt be obedient to him. So that this waſhing did admit them, and ingage them to be his Diſciples, to be taught, and inſtructed by him, and to learn the way of God perfectly, which they could not but believe he would acquaint them withall, being a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſent by God unto them. And this is moſt plainly intimated in the words of that commiſſion Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto them. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go and teach,</hi> or diſciple <hi>all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> Where there are two teachings, the one before, the other after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the firſt can be no more then a perſwaſion of them to become the Diſciples of Chriſt, and put themſelves
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121307:41"/>
into his ſchool, becauſe he was the Son of God; and then after they were baptized, follows a more accurate and full inſtruction of them in all the parts of their Duty, which is meant by thoſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you.</hi> Where the word for teaching is different from that in the former verſe, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a larger knowledge of Chriſts Doctrine which they had ingaged themſelves to obſerve, being aſſured the Son of God could teach them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Truth.</p>
            <p>And this I take to be the reaſon why ſo many fell off again from this profeſſion, when the diſpleaſing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Chriſt came to be practiſed. They had not conſidered what it would coſt them to be Chriſtians, but only as I ſaid, were in general convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he was Gods Son, and that they muſt be his Diſciples, and ſo they liked no longer to be his followers, when their carnal Intereſts came to be touched, and when they ſaw that he was ſuch a Maſter as would not let them have their own will, nor enjoy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121307:41"/>
this preſent world, nor (in one word,) ſerve two Maſters, God and their Mammon too. Though they did in groſs (as I ſaid,) profeſs to forſake their ſins, and lead a holy life, yet when they came to be informed in the particulars of ſelf-denial, and ſuch hard leſſons, they returned rather with the dog to the vomit,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> and the waſhed ſow to the wallowing in the mire.</p>
            <p>That I may put an end to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, let me ſhew you a little how it will be uſefull to you, and have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon practiſe, and if you be believing, and obedient, I ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident I have not made you miſpend an hour in peruſing what I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented.</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>TAke notice of the great Wiſdom of our Lord, that though he have left us an outward Ceremony ſtill in his Church, yet it is ſuch an one, that ſignifies not one thing, but the whole Religion, and not only ſignifies, but ingages us unto our duty. You have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121307:42"/>
ſeen that Baptiſm expreſſeth the whole Covenant of Grace between God and us, and whereas the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſeveral Rites and uſages, to ſet forth and repreſent ſeveral duties, Chriſt hath left us only this, (together with the Bread and Wine in the other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,) which are ſuch as are eaſie to be had, and to be practiſed, and are ſimple, plain, &amp; eaſie to be underſtood, and do alſo ſhew us our whole Duty, and likewiſe lay Ingagements upon us to perform it; ſo that we cannot uſe either of them, but thereby we are bound to be wholly Gods, and intirely devoted to his ſervice. And therefore,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, Let me ſtrongly plead with you in the behalf of God, to take heed to your ſelves, and your wayes according to his Word. You are all baptized into Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you have put on Chriſt, you have ſolemnly ingaged your ſelves to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godlily in this preſent evil world;<note place="margin">Gal. 5.3.</note> and as the Apoſtle
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121307:42"/>
ſaith of Circumciſion, ſo I ſay to you, <hi>I teſtifie to every man that is baptized, that he is a Debtor to obſerve the whole Goſpel.</hi> What then have you to do with the Devil whom you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced? Why are you ſo in love with the world, which you have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, and from which you are divorc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Why are you ſo tender of the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of the fleſh, which you promiſed to mortifie, and crucifie together with Chriſt? What is the reaſon that you renounce Chriſt in your lives, as if you were aſhamed of his profeſſion?</p>
               <p>Is Baptiſm but a cold Ceremony? or do you think the waſhing of the fleſh will ſave you? Not only the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle confutes you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. but you ſhall hear your ſelves put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence out of the mouth of a very <hi>Jew, He that believeth not as he ought</hi> (ſaith the Author of the book, <hi>Nitzachon,) his Circumciſion doth not make him a</hi> Jew; <hi>but he that doth believe aright,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Joſeph. de Voyſin de leg. Div. <hi>cap. 44.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is a</hi> Jew, <hi>though he be not circumciſed.</hi> One would not expect ſuch language from them that glory in Circumciſion: but God hereby ſhames ſuch outward Profeſſors that glory in Baptiſm, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121307:43"/>
they did in Circumciſion, though they be not the followers of faithfull <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> As long as their ears, and tongue,<note place="margin">Exo. 6.12. Jer. 6.10. Jer. 9.26.</note> and heart were uncircumciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (for of all thoſe we read,) their fore-skin remained, and as long as our thoughts, and words, and wayes are impure, we are in effect unbaptized.</p>
               <p>If then outward Baptiſm will not ſave, why do you not cleanſe your ſelves from all filthineſs both of fleſh &amp; ſpirit, and perfect holineſs in the fear of God? Do you not at all value the Promiſes of God? Is it no favour to be his Children, to have forgiveneſs of ſins, and an inheritance among thoſe that are ſanctified through faith? Or is there any other way wherein theſe can be attained? Can you find a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cut to heaven by ſome other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage? Aſſure your ſelves, that there is no other Covenant whereby to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of theſe promiſes, but that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which is conſigned by Baptiſm, whereby we ſtand ingaged to the performance of ſuch Duties as our Saviour doth require. We ſhall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably flatter and abuſe our ſelves, if we imagine to come to Heaven any
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121307:43"/>
other way then through the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Baptiſm, wherein we promiſe to forſake all the enemies of God, and to adhere and cleave to him faithfully and loyally againſt all the perſwaſion: and temptations of the devil, world and fleſh; and therefore unleſs we can ſhew a new Goſpel, and be baptized over again by the appointment of God, and obtain ſome eaſier, and more pleaſing conditions, let us arm our ſelves againſt, and bid defiance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and reſolve that no luſt ſhall eſcape with its life. What, art thou a Chriſtian, and as fond of the pleaſures of the world as a <hi>Pagan?</hi> as loth to diſpleaſe the fleſh, as if thou hadſt been initiated in the impure Myſteries of the heathen; as covetous, as if thou waſt an Idolater, and didſt worſhip a god of Gold? as ſenſual, beaſtly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh in thy affections, paſſions and converſation, as if thou waſt ſome black <hi>African,</hi> and hadſt never been <hi>inlightned?</hi> Oh! Do not live as if thou hadſt been baptized in the Devils name, and hadſt ſworn to be his bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and entered a Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtution againſt God and Chriſt, and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121307:44"/>
with Heaven. O live not I beſeech you, as if it were your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for to ſin; as if you had been baptized in a ditch, and waſhed with puddle water, and had profeſſed to be as dirtily and baſely imployed, as ever you were able. Did your Baptiſm ſignifie that you ſhould be drowned in drink, that you ſhould be buried vilely and covetouſly in the earth; that you ſhould riſe and lift up your head againſt heaven; that you ſhould fill the air with oaths &amp; blaſphemies, and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom ſpeeches, and that you ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God, and all above? No, the Devil himſelf durſt not urge a Witch to make ſuch a Covenant with him; and therefore his Art and Subtilty is to make men live after this prophane ſort, though they make not ſuch a profeſſion: and he labours to baptize and drench their ſouls in this belief, that the Covenant of Grace ſignifies all on Gods part, nnd nothing at all on theirs. They are even ſwallowed up in theſe conceits, that they ſhall enjoy pardon, grace and ſalvation, and be priviledged from wrath to come; and in the mean time, take care only to do as they pleaſe, to live <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121307:44"/>
Heathens phraſe is,) <hi>a moiſt, ſoft and delicate life,</hi> and to ſwim to Heaven in rivers of pleaſure, and carnal delights. What ſwarms and herds of followers ſhould a man have that went about, and preached ſuch a Baptiſm for the commiſſion of ſins? but there is no need any one ſhould do the Devil that ſervice; for the Baptiſm of Chriſt is made one of his myſteries, and all our preaching cannot root out this belief, that Chriſt will be the Author of eternal ſalvation to them that do not obey him. But 'tis as clear as the Light, that a Covenant is between two perſons, and both are ingaged to ſome perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; and that God is no otherwiſe bound in this baptiſmal Covenant, then we are bound alſo: and that he gives pardon upon no other conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but theſe, that we forſake the Devil, the World, and all the luſts of the fleſh. If we therefore renounce this part, then we diſcharge him of all that he hath promiſed. And the truth is, it is very ridiculous to imagine, that God ſhould waſh us there clean, that ever after we might be as ſoul as we pleaſe. As if a <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Chriſtian,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121307:45"/>
who ſpits upon the ground withindig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, when he renounces the Devil in Baptiſm ſhould preſently fall down, and lick it up again. Or, as if one ſhould put on a Garment of light, be clad with a white robe, that he might ſweep chimnies, and rake in kennels, or lead dung-carts about the ſtreets. If we be the Children of the Light, then we muſt have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſs, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire our ſelves in the filth and dirt of the world. If we be Chriſts Diſciples, we muſt not only make a face, and ſpit when we hear the Devil named, but we muſt abhor his works, and defie all his filthy luſts, and have our very ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack riſe at all that comes from hell. And ſo men would, were they not jugled into a belief that they defie the Devil, while he embraces them in his arms. I remember a ſtory in the life of a <hi>Romiſh Religious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalena de Patſi.</note> how that ſhe ſhould ſee one day in a viſion the ſoul of a ſinner dragged to hell, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the mercy of purgatory, <hi>for not having in account the ſpiritual trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church, but deſpiſing both indulgences, and all other graces which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121307:45"/>
ſhe grants her Children.</hi> So doth the Devil labour to nurſe in mens hearts a perſwaſion that outward things can ſave them, and that he can do them no harm, if they be baptized, keep the Church, ſay their prayers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Miniſters bleſſing, which is all they think that Baptiſm ingages them unto; and they make the ſame uſe of Chriſt, that others do of the Pope, thinking to buy a pardon (if they have not one already,) by the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch a holineſs, as the Devil, if he were incarnate, need not be afraid of, but might ſwear he would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. O, what pitty is it, that Chriſt ſhould be thus abuſed, and his inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions perverted, and ſouls undone, when it is ſo plain, what he would have us to do that we may be ſaved!</p>
               <p>But will not ſome little ſprinklings of holineſs ſerve the turn, may ſome ſay? May we not allow ſome place for ſelf-pleaſing, and gratifie our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſometimes, ſeeing we wallow not alwayes in filthineſs? No, Baptiſm, though only upon the face, ſignifies the waſhing of the whole man from ſpiritual pollutions, and though only
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121307:46"/>
once adminiſtred, puts us into a ſtate of purity, which muſt not willingly admit of any defilement. And let thoſe men know that have their good moods, their cold fits of Repentance, and their hot fits of zeal, that uſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do holy water, when they are entring into the Church, and going to perform ſome devotion; that Chriſt owns no ſuch Diſciples. They were not baptized in luke-warm water, but were ingaged in a ſtate of mortification, and entred into Chriſts death, and he expects a conſtant performance of obedience.<note place="margin">Aelian. l. <hi>4.</hi> var. hiſt. <hi>cap. 1.</hi>
                  </note> There were a people in <hi>Illyricum,</hi> that were waſhed but three times in all their lives, at their birth, at their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, &amp; at their death. And they may be a picture of moſt Chriſtians amongſt us, who in their Infancy are waſhed in Chriſts nam; and then perhaps againſt ſome ſolemn time, when the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is near, they begin to put away their ſins, and perhaps baptize themſelves in tears, and deck up themſelves, as though they would meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, and be married unto him; and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121307:46"/>
of this you ſhall hear no more, (unleſs at ſuch a time as that,) till death tell them that he can ſtay no longer, and ſome ſickneſs arreſts them, then they begin to ſlubber and cry, to ſigh and groan, as if by tears they could waſh away their guilt, and by a few ſighs and good wiſhes, blow away the black cloud of wrath that hangs over their heads. They make Religion to be a few ſtrong pang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of devotion at certain times of their life, and Chriſt to be pleaſed with any thing, glad of any company, and heaven to be an empty void place that wants Inhabitants, much like to the new found world, whither we ſend the moſt raſcal peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But Chriſt will ſhortly appear to all the world, to confute all ſuch men, and he will drench them in ſeas of fire, the floods of his wrath ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them, and they ſhall never riſe again.</p>
               <p>But is there ſuch great danger then, may ſome ſay? Will not God be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more favourable to us then other men, and will not the waters of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> a little quench and cool the flames?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121307:47"/>Cool them? No, they will be like water upon lime, which will make it burn the hotter. Even this will be pleaded againſt you, that you were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. If a Souldier ſworn to <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould forſake his Camp, and flie to the <hi>Turks,</hi> would he not be puniſhed more then a ſtranger when he was taken, and ſuffer as a falſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fellow, as a Run-agate, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured perſon? Who would admit of ſuch a plea from his mouth? I am no forſworn Wretch, I never denyed <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> nor renounced my Allegiance to him; no man ever heard me ſpeak a word againſt him: Might it not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be returned to him, but thou didſt deny him in thy Actions, thou haſt more then forſworn him, for thou haſt fought againſt him, yea, thou haſt joined with a Tyrant, with the greateſt enemy the Emperor hath, and the ſworn foe of all Chriſtians; if ſuch a Fellow ſhould live, who ſhould die? What is the Ax and the Gibbet made for, if not for ſuch trayterous Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains? The Gallows would think much, if thou ſhouldſt be reprieved. Thou readeſt thy own caſe, O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, if thou liveſt in ſin, and fideſt with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121307:47"/>
the Devil, and takeſt thy ſhare with the world, whom thou haſt renounced in word, but not in deed. What though thou doſt not call the Lord Chriſt a <hi>Deceiver?</hi> What though thou doſt not revile the holy name whereby we are called? thou doſt a great deal worſe, thou bendeſt all thy forces thou haſt againſt him, as if he were a thief and a Robber, thou laboureſt to deſtroy his Kingdom, thou trampleſt under foot the blood of the Covenant, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chriſt unto thee of none effect. Which is the worſt enemy, he that ſpeaks thee fair, and with a kiſs ſtabs thee to the heart? or he that bids thee ſtand upon thy guard, and declares himſelf reſolv'd againſt thy life? I will aſſure you <hi>Turks</hi> are not ſuch enemies to Chriſt, as thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to him, and yet do him all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight they can in their lives. Better had it been for them that ſome band of ſouldiers had raviſhed them from their mothers breaſts, and liſted them under <hi>Mahomets</hi> banners; better had it been for them to have been <hi>Janiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> then to own and acknowledge the Chriſtian Profeſſion, and live ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121307:48"/>
prophanely without God in the world.</p>
               <p>Heathens may ſin at a cheaper rate then we, becauſe they never made any ſuch Promiſe unto God. They may do evil with a better front, and more confident countenance, that never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any ſuch mark in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. But a Chriſtian face which is beſprinkled with clean water in the name of Chriſt, ſhould bluſh (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks,) at any impurity; and the mark of Chriſt that is upon him ſhould make him more modeſt then to ſin. But if he will beſmear himſelf again, and have the impudence to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face Chriſt, he ſhall pay dearly for it. For he breaks his vow to God, and thereby comes under the curſe which is annexed to the Covenant, as well as the Promiſe. And all theſe terrible threatning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt which in baptiſm he promiſed to believe, as well as any other Word of God, ſhall all fall upon his head, and he ſhall be caſt into a lake indeed but it is a lake burning with fire and brimſtone.<note place="margin">Rev. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.8.</note> Better had it been for ſuch an one, if he had been drowned in the font, or entred into the gates of death, when he entred into the gates of the Church, it had been better for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121307:48"/>
him, if he had been branded with a hot iron in his fore-head, or ſcalding oil had been poured upon his face, when it was waſhed with water in the name of Chriſt. The flames of hell ſhall eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally burn and conſume without any conſumption that filthy ſoul, whoſe dirt the waters of Baptiſm, and the fires of the holy Ghoſt could not fetcht out, and ſcour away. And if any complain of their weakneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>THirdly, Here is matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to us. We are in a Covenant of Grace, there is a Redemption for us if we have a mind to be delivered; we have aſſurance of the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, and if we be ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watchfull and diligent, he will not, becauſe of our failings, take away his Holy Spirit from us. Through the Spirit of Chriſt we ſhall be able to do valiantly, nothing ſhall be too hard to overcome, but we ſhall tread all our enemies under our feet.</p>
               <p>Let us march out therefore as the Souldiers of Chriſt, carrying his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121307:49"/>
Croſs in our Banners; let us profeſs, and declare that we are crucified to the world, that we are buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm,<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 6</note> and reckon our ſelves to be dead indeed unto ſin, <hi>But alive unto God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Let not ſin therefore reign in your mortal bodies, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof; neither yield ye your members as Inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs unto ſin, but yield your ſelves unto God, as thoſe that are alive from the dead, and your members as inſtruments of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs unto God. For ſin ſhall not have dominion over you, for you are not under the Law, but under Grace. It is a ſhame now to be overcome, when you ſerve under ſuch a Captain, and have Heaven on your ſide, and have received the promiſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt Is there no power in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God? or is not God as good as his word? Will not he give us what he hath promiſed, to make us to vanquiſh all his enemies? O do not ſpeak ſuch evil things of God by doing any evil. Do not diſgrace your profeſſion, nor bring a diſhonour upon your Lord, by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121307:49"/>
letting every temptation uſe you at its pleaſure. Do not ſuffer every luſt to foil and worſt you, as if you were Turks and Infidels, and had none of the mark or badge of God upon you, and as if your Baptiſm was of no more avail to you, then the waſhing of your hands. But firſt reſolve that all theſe luſts of the fleſh muſt be overcome, and then conclude that they may. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelves that God is with you, and that he hath appointed no ineffectual Rites, no bare ſhadows, no beggerly Ceremonies, and cold For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities in the Religion of Chriſt; but that if you uſe your Diligence, and pray continually, you ſhall find the holy Ghoſt to accompany you, and that you are born again, not of water only, but of the Spirit, and ſhall final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inherit eternal life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That you may receive greater ſupplies of the ſpirit promiſed, and be more ingaged to your duty, labour fully to underſtand your vow and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and then come, and openly own it, profeſſing you will be faithfull to it, that ſo you may be admitted to nearer familiarity with God. Let me
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121307:50"/>
prevail with all young perſons who are yet in the gate of the Church, and have proceeded no further then to be baptized in their Infancy, and perhaps to be catechized in the principles of Religion, to ſpend a few thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this which I propound. For though outward Baptiſm, which is the viſible ſign and ſeal of the Covenant,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21.</note> is not to be renewed, yet the Anſwer of a good conſcience, wherein the inward Baptiſm doth conſiſt, may, and ought to be re-iterated by a perſonal reſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ratification of that vow which was made for us in our infant years. And no man is to be reputed a compleat member of the Church, untill he do own his Ingagements, and openly profeſs that he will ſtand to the conditions of the Covenant, and be a Diſciple of Chriſt. If Baptiſm did at firſt admit us into the injoyment of many priviledges, ſurely we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more of the bleſſings of it, when we do ſeriouſly reflect upon it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our hearts by our own free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to God, becauſe then we begin more ſolemnly to perform the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that God requireth of us. When
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121307:50"/>
I firſt entred upon a charge of ſouls, I could think of no courſe ſo anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently atteſted unto, ſo reaſonable in it ſelf, and ſo likely to be effectual for mens good, ſo free likewiſe from the juſt exceptions of any party, as to propoſe this to my people, that all thoſe who had not yet been commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, ſhould freely and heartily in the preſence of thoſe who were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at any time to partake of the Lords Supper, profeſs to be ſincere and conſtant in their baptiſmal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and declare themſelves enemies to the Devil, the world, and the fleſh. And I will take occaſion here to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I am heartily glad that Mr. <hi>Hanmer</hi> hath propoſed this; and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſo earneſtly preſſed it upon the whole Nation; after whoſe pious and learned endeavours, let me contribute my little Mite to the urging thoſe, into whoſe hands this ſmall Treatiſe ſhall come, that they would not refuſe it. This Chriſtian Duty hath long paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under the name of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which is a word full, and ſignificant of the thing that I. would expreſs, and conſiſts of two parts. Firſt, That a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121307:51"/>
perſon do undertake in his own name every part of the vow made by others for him in Baptiſm, and ſo perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſent unto Chriſt to be wholly his, according to that agreement. And ſo it is an Act of <hi>Confirmation</hi> on our part, becauſe we do hereby further ratifie and eſtabliſh that contract which is between God and us, and by confeſſing of it to be valid and good, bind our ſelves faſter ſtill to him, whoſe we were before. The ſecond part of it is; A receiving of Gods Bleſſing and Grace by the Miniſters hands, and holy prayers, to ſtrengthen us to perform our Engagement, and make good our word and faith which we have plighted unto God; which many have taken to be the meaning of that place,<note n="(*)" place="margin">Beſide ſundry of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Beza, Piſcator, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nnius, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yricus, Toſſanus, G ynaeus,</hi> do ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it. See alſo <hi>Hyperius</hi> and <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ling.</hi> In <hi>loc.</hi> who wiſh for the reſtoring of it in thoſe Churches from which it had been baniſhed.</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. Where after Baptiſm, follows, laying on of hands, which the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed in their bleſsings. And ſo it is an <hi>Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> of the perſon on the part of God, who confers a new grace to ſtrengthen, and confirm in him theſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121307:51"/>
holy Principles, and that good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which he hath made a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full profeſsion, and to inable him to keep and perſiſt in it. As in Baptiſm, the Holy Ghoſt was conveyed as a Sanctifier, ſo herein as a Comforter and Strengthner now, that the perſon is entring upon a great conteſt and conflict with himſelf, the world, and principalites, and powers, and ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places. The neceſsity of this is not now in this age of the world, as a new thing to be learned; there never could be a well conſtituted Church without it, nor can we tell that men are not Heathens, and have not revoked their word, unleſs they will tell us they underſtand what they then did, and will not ſtir from it. But if it be viſible ſouls are not like in any great numbers to be ſaved without ſome ſuch courſe, (ſo many attending upon Sermons many years that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand little or nothing,) it will not be diſputed by ſober men, whether it be neceſſary or no; and for proof of this, I refer to the better works of him that labours more abundantly then us all;<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
                  </note> thinking it ſufficient for one to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121307:52"/>
perſwade, what abler men do prove. Let me only produce the teſtimony of a very great and learned perſon lately in this Church, and add it to the words of the R. and learned <hi>D. Hammond,</hi> which you find at the end of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> book. <hi>For all ſuch as have been baptized in their Infancy, the perſonal Reſumption and Ratification of that Vow which their fathers and mothers in God did make for them at the ſacred Laver,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. l.</hi> 10. upon the Creed. <hi>Cap.</hi> 50. To which add the words of another more anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the end of this Treatiſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its length, not here inſerted.</note> 
                  <hi>is to be exacted of them</hi> Ore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenus, <hi>in ſome publique congregation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can lawfully be admitted to be publique Communicants of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood.</hi> And though he can find no default in the Doctrine, or Laws of our Church, yet (he ſaith,) he dare not avouch ſo much for juſtifying the men, to whom the execution of thoſe Laws is commended, whether they be of lower, of higher, or of the higheſt rank. It having been ſcarce in his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that any preſentments were made in viſitations, <hi>of the parents,</hi> for not bringing perſons to; <hi>or of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> for not preparing them for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, much leſs againſt <hi>Dioceſans</hi> themſelves for not executing their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121307:52"/>
Office in this <hi>great ſervice</hi> of the Church. And he concludes in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable words, <hi>Whether the ſolemn baptizing of all Infants, which are the Children of preſumed Chriſtian parents throughout this Kingdom, without ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſtipulation, that they ſhal at years of Diſcretion perſonall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ratifie their vow in Baptiſm in publique, in ſuch manner as the Church requires, be not rather more lawfull, or tolerable, then expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, I leave with all ſubmiſſion to the conſideration of higher powers.</hi> And he bleſſes God that he was in a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent age, in a happy time and place, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ratifie his vow made for him by his ſureties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſure he would not have done, if he had not found it very beneficial unto his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good and welfare.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author hath theſe words in a Treatiſe publiſhed in his life time,<note place="margin">Treatiſe of Faith <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>g.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He that ſets his hand unto the ſacred plough, ſhould firſt begin to ſound the depth of that rule,</hi> What it is to deny our ſelves, and forſake all we have, <hi>for in this furrow muſt the ſeed of life be ſown. Here Novices in Religion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly begin to balk, and no wonder, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121307:53"/>
ſo few are called to any ſtrict perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal accompt of that which others have undertaken for them at their firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Bed-roll of Chriſtians. But if that treble vow</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> made in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>were diſtinctly and fully unfolded unto us, as ſoon as we had any knowledge of good and evil; and all the ſeveral branches of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, with as great care and ſolemnity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated, as</hi> Moſes <hi>commanded the Law ſhould be to the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>Children: And laſtly, The Vow it ſelf confirmed and ratified by our perſonal proteſtation in the ſight of the Congregation; the fear as well of God, as of ſhame before men, in whoſe preſence we made this profeſſion, would bind many of us to more Chriſtian behaviour, then the beſt of us, as the world goes, dare make ſhew of; as alſo reſtrain us from many deadly Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which now admoniſhed of, we will not accompt any ſins. Thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receive it, it would be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much infidelity to diſtruſt the plentifull Infuſion of inherent ſanctifying Grace at our ſolemnities of Confirmation; were theſe firſt ſanctified with publique prayers, or performed with ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian care and diligence as they ought.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121307:53"/>
A religious Duty in the Chriſtian Church, which it were to be wiſhed, might be performed more often, more ſolemnly, and more religiouſly then it uſeth to be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed who ſees not that great benefits would hence flow,<note place="margin">See the teſtimony annexed at the end of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note> both to particular perſons, and to the Church of God? It would be a means to make men more knowing in the things of their ſalvation, to tie them more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to mind the affairs of their ſouls, to work in them a deeper ſenſe of the great buſineſs of being a Chriſtian. It would make men more afraid to commit a ſin againſt which they had ſo ſolemnly and publiquely proteſted. It would bring Religion to be a thing credible and more in faſhion then it is, when men did ſo openly appear for it, and ingage themſelves unto it. It is at once acceptable to God, and ſafe to our ſelves, and ſo will be accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Grace, and in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cut off many inticements of the world. It will bid us ſtand upon our Reputation in the purſuit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and not run the hazard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perjured perſons. Wicked men
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121307:54"/>
will not have the confidence to ask us to ſin, when we have ſo publiquely diſowned them. You complain of evil company, of friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance that ingage you; do but let them know that you intend to be religious, and they will let you alone. The Philoſophers openly profeſſed a ſevere and unuſnal life, that all men might let them live philoſophically, and not be a diſturbance unto them; Let but us do ſo, and be profeſſedly religious, and ſolemnly tell all men that we mean to keep our vows, and they will have the leſs boldneſs for to trouble us. Our work is half done, when we are heartily reſolved; and more then half, when we profeſs theſe reſolutions. It will bring us to mans eſtate, that we may feed at the Table of the Lord, whereby we may increaſe in ſtrength, and have more near com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Father, Son and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. Though I will not ſay, that till this be done, men are members of the Church imperfectly, yet I muſt needs think, that they are but imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect members, they are but babes and infants in Chriſt, and not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121307:54"/>
(in the Judgement of all ages,) to taſt of the meat of men, till they ſhew themſelves to be men, by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for themſelves. In ſhort, it will be a great ſecurity and defence againſt temptations, and we ſhall recoil upon our ſelves, when we are aſſaulted, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, How ſhall we do this wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kedneſs, and break our vows, and ſcandalize the Church, and bring the guilt of perjury upon our own ſouls?</p>
               <p>It is obſerved by <hi>Joſ. de Voyſin</hi> out of the Author of the book <hi>Ikkarim,</hi> that the elevation of the hands of the Prieſt in the old Law at the bleſſing of the people, was impoſition of hands; and this bleſſing the Author of <hi>Tze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror Hammor</hi> cals the <hi>Weapons and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Iſrael,</hi> the Artilery (as it were,) and the Bulwarks of his people. I will aſſure you that this ſolemn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, together with Gods Grace and bleſſing that will deſcend upon you, will be your great guard and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, your ſword and buckler to beat off temptations that are apt moſt ſtrongly to aſſault your younger years, before you have had experience of the worlds vanity. Therefore he that
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121307:55"/>
would not be without a ſhield in the midſt of fiery darts, he that would not be weak and feeble among ſtrong ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that would not be a prey to the Devil and the World, let him come, and put himſelf under the wings of the divine Majeſty, by his own actual conſent, let him give up himſelf into the hands of God, to be kept by his Power through faith unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>There is nothing can hinder any man from embracing this motion, but that which will hinder men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorough Chriſtians, and living godly in Chriſt Jeſus: And we may be confident, that none are fit to receive the Sacrament of Chriſts body and blood, that are not willing to ſubmit unto it. For he that hungers after the ſweeter taſts of Chriſts love, that deſires to unite his heart more cloſely to him, and to ingage himſelf more firmly in the Covenant of God by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the remembrances of his love, will not refuſe to do that in word, which he intends to do in deed. If he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mean to be a Profeſſor of Chriſts Religion, and to teſtifie to the world,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121307:55"/>
that the deeds thereof are evil, and contradict their manners in his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, then he will not ſtick to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them in his words, and renounce them ſolemnly by his mouth, which is the far eaſier matter.</p>
               <p>Will any man be aſhamed to make ſuch a profeſſion, and to tread in the way of Chriſts Church, becauſe it hath been of late diſuſed, or turned into another thing? Why ſhouldſt thou bluſh to own holineſs, to ſay before Chriſts Church, thou art reſolved to lead a Chriſtian life, and renounce the Devil, and all the wayes of wickedneſs? Why ſhouldſt thou be aſhamed of thy Religion, as though it were fit to be profeſſed only in a private corner, where none ſhould hear thee? Why ſhould it be accounted a ſtrange thing to proteſt love to God? It is an honour and glory to us, that we may be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſo we ſhould eſteem it. We ſhould be glad, if we can do our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſo much honour as to confeſs him openly before men, that ſo he may confeſs us before all his H. Angels. We may be confident, that we ſhall never in a time of perſecution confeſs him,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121307:56"/>
(of Which theſe places in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſpeak,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.32. Mar. 8.38. Rom. 10.8, 9, 10.</note>) if we cannot be perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do it among the Children of Peace? Will any one be aſhamed that it ſhould be told by the Miniſter, that ſuch an one declared himſelf a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and hath to me avowed his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſolemnly ſaid, that he will by the Grace of God make good his baptiſmal promiſe? Will any one be loth it ſhould be publiquely ſaid, that he is a Chriſtian? Why then ſhould he not ſay ſo himſelf? Suppoſe you were not yet baptized, or had lived in the firſt times, and heard Chriſt preached, would you be unwilling to come, and proſeſs that you renounced the Devil, the World, and their luſts? Shall none own the Religion of Chriſt publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but Infants that cannot underſtand it? The more we know, ſhall we be the more loth to declare our liking of his wayes? Are you unwilling to repreſent the childs perſon, and profeſs publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it in the congregation? Why ſhould you not do that for your ſelves which you are willing to do for others? Cannot he that comes in the name of a child, and ſaith, <hi>I believe,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121307:56"/>
&amp;c. <hi>I renounce,</hi> &amp;c. come, and do the ſame in his own name? I do really think, that they that are unwilling to undertake Chriſts Profeſſion by an open promiſe, would not be baptized if it had not been done in their Infant years, they would remain rather Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Infidels, then be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of God, for upon no lower conditions then theſe are, could they ever have been admitted to any Chriſtian priviledges. Unleſs therefore you will ſhew your ſelves to want all underſtanding, and not fit to be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as men of common reaſon, put not away from you ſo many Intreaties. If you think your Baptiſm to be worth your owning, if you would not really be without it, and take your ſelves to be the better for it, renew ſolemnly that League and Promiſe with God, and do not perſwade your ſelves and others, that you prize the Baptiſm, while you are unwilling unto this, for if that were not done, you would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly omit it as a needleſs Ceremony, as well as this which alwayes accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed it in the Church of Chriſt.<note n="*" place="margin">Anton. de Dom. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Eccleſ.</note> Seeing nothing can reaſonably be thought
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121307:57"/>
to make you unwilling, but a lothneſs to be good, and ingaged to live well; do not by refuſing, caſt an Aſperſion upon your ſelves of having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Chriſt, and ſecretly entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a confoederacy with the Devil to deſtroy his Kingdom, and trample under foot his blood as an unholy thing.</p>
               <p>When this confirmation was lookt upon by the multitude as a means only to receive ſome thing from God, but not as laying any obligation upon men; it was a wonder (I ſhould have ſaid no wonder,) to ſee what flocks and herds of people came unto it. In <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes, (as <hi>Saunders</hi> tell us.<note place="margin">De Schiſm.</note>) when this cuſtom by a provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial decree of <hi>Card. Pooles</hi> was renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after long neglect, the people were ſo zealous to receive the Biſhops bleſsing,<note place="margin">There were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees long before to inforce it, as that of <hi>Archb. Peckham. An.</hi> 1271. Wherein he calls the diſuſe of it, <hi>Damnable Negligence.</hi>
                  </note> (which was all they went for,) that in ſome places the Church could not contain the people that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to him, and he was fain to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm in the Church-yard, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121307:57"/>
by armed men from the preſs of the multitude.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould not men come now in as great Crowds, when another renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in a more ſolemn manner is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed? Why ſhould not the young people aſſemble themſelves together, and ſay, <hi>Come, Let us go to the houſe of the Lord, let us own Chriſt to be our Lord and Saviour,</hi> but only becauſe men are loth to be ingaged to fear God, and do love a Chriſt of their own making that ſhall do all for them, and require them to do nothing for him? If God will have men as they are, they can be content to afford him their company; but if he expect any amendment, they deſire to be excuſed from making him any promiſe of it, and hope that they ſhall find him ſo kind in the concluſion, as not to exact it. May not he be well ſatisfied without any bond from us, when (in mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) he will never demand the Debt? Why ſhould we paſs our word for that which will never be required? ſeeing God can bear with mens rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, why ſhould his Miniſters be ſo
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121307:58"/>
rigid, as to exact an Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? Theſe are the thoughts of mens hearts, that God will croſs all ſcores at the laſt, and then to what purpoſe is it to make any ſuch ſerious Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? If we had a window into mens breaſts, we ſhould ſee this Principle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on their hearts, <hi>That the Goſpel is Promiſes, and all their work is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them to be true,</hi> and ſo there need not ſo much be done, as to make an open profeſſion of this belief.</p>
               <p>If Popery ſhould again prevail in <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch a decree ſhould be again revived, what would theſe men do? Would they be ſo backward as now they are to preſent themſelves before the Congregation of God? It is moſt likely that fear or fancy might make thoſe men receive their Oyntment in the fore-head, and box on the ear, (as the manner is in their confirmation,) who now will not for the love of God profeſs they hate ſin, and intend to lead a holy life. So conſtantly it falls out, that what hath difficulty in it is refuſed, and all that requires our ſerious attention, upon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121307:58"/>
ſome account or other is rejected, and men would go to Heaven they know not how, and be ſaved from hell, but not from their ſins. Yea, ſome are ſo ignorant, as to call this <hi>a popiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> when it is very plain, that if it were, they would not ſpeak againſt it. If only their Children were to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that underſtand nothing, we might eaſily perſwade them to ſend them, when as they will rather themſelves remain Children, then make any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenant with God by their own mouths. If a Character (as they ſpeak,) was to be impreſſed, and the benefit to ariſe <hi>ex opere operato</hi> out of the meer doing of the work, they would willingly be ſo ſealed for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but if they muſt ſet their own ſeal to any Ingagements, they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their hands, and will preſume upon ſome other way of conveyance, and making over Gods great Bleſſings to them. If they can be ſaved by ſprinkling water on their face, and the woman can carry them in her arms to Heaven, as ſhe doth unto the Font; they are content, it coſts them no trouble at all. But if it were to do
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121307:59"/>
again, if it muſt coſt them Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, a holy life, and a hearty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, they would ſcorn that Baptiſm wherein now they truſt ſo much, and they would rather venture to be as they were born, then be waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their pollutions on ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. O that men would take theſe things at leaſt ſo far into their thoughts, as to paſs a ſerious Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them, whether they be true or falſe! Do not read theſe lines with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a little pauſe. And then go on, and conſider with thy ſelf, how unlikely it is, that they, who even break their brains with ſtudy to do men good, and ſigh till their heart ake after mens ſalvation, ſhould be the greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of men, the troublers of their Peace, and that love to perſwade them needleſs or indifferent things, that may as well be left undone.</p>
               <p>Let ſome honeſt Heathens (for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion) be admitted for to plead the cauſe of this truth, &amp; perhaps they may make thoſe faces bluſh who look on theſe lines, but are loth to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any publique preſence to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their Religion. When the <hi>Perſian</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:121307:59"/>
youth were out of their minority, and came to mens eſtate. They gave them an Oath which they ſolemnly took in this form,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſidor. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuſ.</hi> l. 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 198.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſwear that I will deſpiſe all filthy lucre, bodily ploaſures, and vain glory; that I will rather be aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of vertue, and worſhip God, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence my Parents, ſpeaking Truth, and doing good, neither will I ever witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly violate any of theſe things.</hi> Sure theſe old Heathens would not have refuſed to do what is now deſired, had they imbraced our Religion, who thus amply proteſted, and took their oath that they would be good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julius Pollux</hi> likewiſe relates the like cuſtom among the <hi>Greeks</hi> in the Common-wealth of <hi>Athens.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. 8. cap. 9. and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Stobaei ſerm.</hi> 41.</note> When their young men were twenty years of age, their names were inſcribed in the City-rolls,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> and they ſwore in the open air, (as if they would have all the world to hear them,) <hi>I will never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace my arms, nor forſake my fellow-ſouldier in his danger; I will fight both alone, and with others for God and my Country, I will ſail to any Region of the world whither I am commanded, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121307:60"/>
will neither diſturb, nor betray my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, I will obſerve the perpetual ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and obey the received cuſtomes, and all that ſhall be hereafter made; I will defend, and ever have in reverence</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the Religion in which I was born;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Gods are witneſſes of theſe things.</hi> Will not you Chriſtians then promiſe thus much to your Lord, now that you are of age, to fight againſt all his enemies, to be true to God, and to him, and that you will never diſhonour your profeſsion, nor forſake the communion of Saints, nor deny him any ſervice that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, nor neglect the Solemnities that he hath appointed? Then may the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Athenians</hi> riſe up in the Judgement againſt you, and condemn you.</p>
               <p>Do men refuſe the oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to their Prince, whoſe natural Subjects they are, and under whoſe Protection they have been born and bred? Would you deny to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in open Court an Inſtrument for your Act and Deed, which was ſigned in your name in Infancy, and conveighs great benefits unto you? Let
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121307:60"/>
the King of Heaven then have ſo much right done him. Let your own ſouls be the greateſt part of your care, and let it not be ſaid, that a rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will do that for an acre of Land, which he will not do to obtain Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all the territories above. What joy would it cauſe in Heaven and Earth to ſee men coming to deſire communion on theſe conditions, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold men crowding into the Kingdom of Heaven, as they do into a Church, and longing after the food of the faithfull, as they do for meat and drink? Rejoyce I beſeech you the heart of God, refreſh the ſouls of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and add to the ſweetneſs of the table of the Lord, by letting us have more good company at ſo joyfull a Feaſt. But if all Intreaties cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail,</p>
               <p>I think the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> had beſt enact a Law, <hi>That none ſhall be marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, till they be inſtructed and confirmed, and that will do it.</hi> For thoſe that care not whether they receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts body and blood, or no, will not live without this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as in a large ſenſe it may be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121307:61"/>
called,) though they underſtand the ends and duties of it no more then of the other. And this muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to have been a great cauſe of our Diſorders, that men enter into theſe relations before they know the duties of them, and beget, and bring forth Children, before they ceaſe to be children themſelves, or know how to bring them up as they ſhould. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Reformers, it is plain, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men ſhould not marry before they were well catechized, and had taken their Baptiſmal vow upon themſelves, knowing, that thoſe were unfit to make a Covenant with each other, who knew not the Covenant of their God. For they preſcribe in the laſt Rubrick of the office of Matrimony, that the perſons new married, muſt that day receive the Communion; and in the laſt Rubrick about Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſay in expreſs words. <hi>That none ſhall be admitted to the holy Communion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as they can ſay the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, and be confirmed.</hi> Let me ſpeak to the very ſenſes of vulgar people. Do you not remember the font ſtood at the lower end of the Church, and the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121307:61"/>
Communion-table at the higher? Could you come from the one to the other but by the Pulpit which ſtands in the middle between both? This teaches you (if you will learn,) that you are only entred into the Church, and are but in the beginnings of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by Baptiſm, and that you muſt advance higher by being inſtructed and taught in the faith of Chriſt, and can no otherwiſe be admitted from the lower to the higheſt forms of Chriſtians. Come therefore, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and then profeſs you like this Doctrine, and will be obedient to it; ſo ſhall you come to be men in Chriſt, and taſt of all his dainties, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the fat things of his houſe.<note place="margin">Quod totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſciri non poteſt, ne omittatur totum, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia partis melior eſt ignorantiâ totius.</note> If all will not be granted that is here requeſted, yet do not deny all, but at leſt profeſs to the Miniſter your hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Repentance, and your belief in Chriſt, and the willingneſs to ſubmit unto him, and to be ſaved by him, that he may declare it to all others. And really ſhew that you are come to an adult eſtate, by putting away childiſh things, and living the life of men. A Child (as one ſaith,) looketh only to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121307:62"/>
things preſent, a man looketh to things to come: A child attends only to paſtime and pleaſure, a man hath alſo profit in his conſideration. A child is ready to ſell his Inheritance for a trifle or bable, of which a man maketh a greater account. His carriage and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour likewiſe diſtinguiſheth him, and ſo doth his confidence againſt vulgar bug-bears and affrightments.</p>
               <p>If therefore after you are confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you find your ſelves to think leſs of things preſent, and more of things to come; leſs of this world, and more of the eternal rewards of Godlineſs, and the everlaſting puniſhments of ſin; if you ſcorn to ſell your heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance for the trifles of this world that preſent themſelves unto you; if you be more attentive to your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual profit in knowledge and mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and not only taken with the ſweetneſſes and raviſhments of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; if your converſation towards God and the world be more ſerious, grave and diſcreet, and you are not ſo eaſily amazed with the fears of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and difficulties in your Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an courſe; it is a ſign that you have
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121307:62"/>
not received the Grace of God in vain, and the Lord will deliver you from every evil work, and preſerve you to his everlaſting Kingdom. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is he that calleth you, who alſo will do it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Let me beſeech all the people of God to live in love and peace together. Let us nor quarrel about every little thing, nor make eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry petty difference a cauſe of trouble and contention. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body.</hi> We are all by this made of the ſame corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and taken by Baptiſm into the ſame Brother-hood, and therefore ſhould not make them the waters of ſtrife, and ſo provoke the Lord to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt us. We are not baptized into this or that particular Opinion, nor received into a particular Church, but into the belief of the Goſpel, and into the Church of God in general, and therefore ſhould love all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples and followers of our Lord, and imbrace all of every perſwaſion that live godlily in Chriſt Jeſus. You were
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121307:63"/>
not baptized (ſaith the Apoſtle) into the name of <hi>Paul,</hi> therefore do not ſay, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I adhere to this man or that, for whoſoever did bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize you, it was not into the particular love of him and his opinions, but into the Communion of the whole Church of Chriſt, who hold the Catholique Faith. Though an <hi>Heretick</hi> in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times had baptized any man, yet did not the Chriſtians therefore bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize him over again when he left thoſe mens company, becauſe being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into the name of Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, he was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the profeſſion of their particular opinions, but of the Truth of Chriſt univerſally believed by all good Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And therefore let us live with them all as our Confederates, as thoſe that are tied together in the ſame bonds, and united in the ſame Covenant, and ingaged in the ſame cauſe againſt the common enemies, the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, and let us never give theſe enemies ſo much cauſe to rejoyce, as an unhandſome word
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121307:63"/>
againſt any ſincere Chriſtian might adminiſter. But let us endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, for as the Apoſtle ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.3, 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, one God and Father of All, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121307:64"/>
            <head>APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE late King</hi> Charls <hi>was confirmed on</hi> EASTER munday,<note place="margin">In the Chappel at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>1613. (which was the thirteenth year of his age,) after</hi> a long and ſtrict Examination <hi>by the</hi> A.B. <hi>of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and the</hi> B. <hi>of</hi> Bath <hi>and</hi> Wells, <hi>as Dr.</hi> George Hackwell, <hi>ear-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſatisfaction he gave, aſſures us; who in a little Tractate, be upon that occaſion wrote on this Subject, to juſtifie the antient and good practiſe of this ſacramental Rite, (as</hi> Bucer <hi>calls it,) thus ſpeaks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 1.</note>Confirmation is an antient Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical cuſtom of the Church, uſed after Baptiſm, conſiſting in Examination and Impoſition of hands, with effectual prayer for the Ilumination of Gods moſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121307:64"/>
holy Spirit, to confirm and perfect that which the Grace of the ſame Spirit hath already begun in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>The benefits of this Confirmation are divers; whereof the firſt is, That men expecting Examination and tryal from their ſpiritual Fathers, they might more willingly acquaint, and carefully ſeaſon themſelves with the grounds of Chriſtian Religion, before malice and corrupt examples depraved their minds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſerves, that when they come to years of Diſcretion, they ſhould publiquely make confeſſion of that faith themſelves which others had promiſed for them in Baptiſm, to the diſcharge of their ſureties, and the good examples of others.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That by ſuch confeſſion they might make profeſſion of difference from all <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> out of the Church; <hi>Hereticks, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and prophane perſons in the Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That then eſpecially when they firſt come to the uſe of Reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to fall into ſundry kinds of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121307:65"/>
ſin, and being leaſt able to reſiſt, for want of experience, by Impoſition of hands and prayer they might receive ſtrength and defence againſt the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That the Prelates and chief Guides of Gods family to whom the cure of ſouls belongeth, finding upon due Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination ſome part of their own heavy burden diſcharged, might from thence reap Comfort in beholding thoſe fair Foundations already laid, and glorifie God, Whoſe praiſe they found in the mouths of Infants.</p>
            <p>This kind of Confirmation (were there no Authority to countenance it,) is in my Judgement ſo uſefull in the Church of God, that upon good reaſon it might be entertained among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: But for further confirmation of it, we are incompaſſed with a cloud of witneſſes, and that ſo plentifully out of all Antiquity, as it might ſeem a kind of Ambition, or loſt labour to quote their names. Wherefore I will only alledge the ſoundeſt of thoſe, who ſince the Reformation of Religion and clearer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121307:65"/>
Light of the Goſpel, in their ſeveral Writings have approved, and highly commended this antient cuſtom. And bringing in <hi>Bucer, Melancton, Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Chemnitius,</hi> and others to ſpeak to this Truth, he cites Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> among the reſt in theſe words. John Calvin <hi>in his fourth Book of</hi> Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <hi>in the</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſhot <hi>of the chapter of</hi> Confirmation,<note place="margin">Cap 19. Para. 13.</note> 
               <hi>not only commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the antient uſe of it, but the abuſe being removed, heartily wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it reſtored.</hi> And becauſe his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is (not without deſert) of great weight, I will ſet down his words as I find them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Would to God (ſaith he) we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that cuſtom which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared to have been in uſe among the Antients, before that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortive Vizard of a Sacrament was put upon it.</hi> And a little after. <hi>If this part of Diſcipline were now a dayes in force, the ſlackneſs of many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents would be much quickened, who paſs over the Inſtitution (or Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) of their Children, as a buſineſs nothing pertaining to them; which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121307:66"/>
then without ſome publique diſgrace they could not omit: Beſides, There would be leſs Ignorance, and more concord in Articles of Faith among Chriſtian people, neither would they ſo eaſily be carried away with new and ſtrange Opinions.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121307:66"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
